<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Eikōn basilikē, or, The princes royal being the sum of a sermon preached in the minister of York on the Lords-Day morning (in the Assize week) March 24, 1650 ... / by John Shavve.</title>
            <author>Shawe, John, 1608-1672.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1650</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 99 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 24 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A59595</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S3028</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R30139</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11249812</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11249812</idno>
            <idno type="VID">47130</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A59595)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 47130)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1450:7)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Eikōn basilikē, or, The princes royal being the sum of a sermon preached in the minister of York on the Lords-Day morning (in the Assize week) March 24, 1650 ... / by John Shavve.</title>
                  <author>Shawe, John, 1608-1672.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>44 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by John Macock for Nathaniel Brooks ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1650.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>First two words of title in Greek characters.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Psalms XLV, 16 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:47130:1"/>
            <p>ΕΙΚΩΝ ΒΑΣΙΛΙΚΗ: OR The Princes Royal: Being the Sum of a SERMON Preached in the Minſter at <hi>York</hi> on the Lords-Day morning (in the Aſsize week) March 24. 1650. before the Right Honorable <hi>Francis Thorp</hi> and <hi>Alexander Rigby,</hi> Eſquires, Barons of the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique Exchequer, and Juſtices of the Aſsize for the Northern Circuit; the Honorable the Lord Major of <hi>York,</hi> the Right Worſhipful Sir <hi>John Savil</hi> Knight, High-Sheriff of <hi>York-ſhire,</hi> the Right Worſhipful Juſtices of Peace, Gentry and others of the City and County of <hi>York.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By JOHN SHAVVE, M. A. Sometimes of Chriſt-Colledg in <hi>Cambridge,</hi> and now Preacher of Gods Word at <hi>Kingston</hi> upon <hi>Hull.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>DAN. 7. 27.</bibl> 
               <hi>And the Kingdom, and Dominion, and the Greatneſs of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom under the whole Heaven, ſhall be given to the People of the Saints of the moſt High, whoſe Kingdom is an everlasting Kingdom, and all Dominions ſhall ſerve and obey him.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>John Macock</hi> for <hi>Nathaniel Brooks,</hi> and are to be ſold at his ſhop at the <hi>Angel</hi> in <hi>Cornhil,</hi> 1650.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:47130:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:47130:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>To the Right Honorable</hi> William Lenthal <hi>
                  <abbr>Eſq</abbr> Speaker of the PARLIAMENT of the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth of ENGLAND.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>RIGHT HONORABLE,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>VEry ancient Hiſtorians call this our Nation <hi>Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mogenitam Eccleſiarum,</hi> the firſt begotten of all the Churches, and tell us that though Chriſt was preached in ſome other Nations before this, yet that this was the firſt wherein the Chriſtian Faith was pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liquely entertained by Prince and State, <hi>Omnium Provinci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arum prima Britannia publicitus Chriſti nomen recepit:</hi> and they add, that <hi>Lucius</hi> King of <hi>Britain</hi> was the firſt Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an King in the world, and did, in the year after Christ, 169. ſend two learned men, <hi>Elvanus</hi> and <hi>Medvinus,</hi> to <hi>Eleutherius</hi> (then Biſhop of <hi>Rome)</hi> to receive further inſtruction in the Chriſtian Faith, and for the better Government of this Land; <hi>Eleutherius</hi> returned Anſwer by two learned men, <hi>Faganus</hi> and <note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Others call them</hi> Fugatius <hi>and</hi> Dimanus.</note> 
               <hi>Damianus,</hi> in theſe words; <q>You require of us the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Laws and the Emperors to be ſent over to you, the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Laws and the Emperors we may ever reprove, but the Law of God we cannot; you have received by Gods Mercy in the Realm of <hi>Britain</hi> the Law and Faith of Chriſt; you have with you within the Realm both the parts of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, the Old and New Teſtament: Out of the ſame by Gods grace, with the counſel of your Realm, take you a Law,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:47130:3"/> and by that Law, through Gods ſufferance, rule you your Kingdom of <hi>Britain;</hi> for a King hath his name of ruling, and not of having a Realm: you ſhall be a King while you rule well, but if you do otherwiſe, the name of a King ſhall not remain with you, and you ſhall loſe it, which God for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid, &amp;c.</q> And though the Gospel was preached here before then, yet not till then were the Temples of Idolatry, the twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty eight Flamines, and three Arch-Flamines removed, and a marvellous great change made throughout <hi>Lucius</hi> his Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, <hi>Romanorum inacceſſa loca, Chriſto fuere ſubdita:</hi> After, when <hi>Gregory</hi> ſent <hi>Auguſtin</hi> the Monk hither, (who brought over ſome Truth and much Superstition) in the <hi>Saxons</hi> reign here, <hi>anno</hi> 596. he found the wife of <hi>Ethelbert</hi> King of <hi>Kent (viz.</hi> Queen <hi>Berta)</hi> and her Chaplain Biſhop <hi>Luidhard</hi> and many others, zealous Chriſtians, especially in <hi>Wales,</hi> yet ſome light broke out then, and much more in the reign of a childe (King <hi>Edward</hi> 6.) and more by a woman (Queen <hi>Elizab.)</hi> that God alone might have all the glory: and ſurely God is carrying on the ſame work ſtill, in purging and reforming of his Church, ſhaking Nations, that Chriſt may the more come in: And I verily beleeve that no ten <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hagg.</hi> 2. 7.</note> years ſince <hi>Lucius</hi> his time can ſpeak of ſo great wonders (if not miracles) wrought for <hi>England,</hi> and wherein the Lord hath more appeared for the good of his People here, then ſince Your Honor hath ſate in the Chair of that Honorable Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly of <hi>Englands Parliament.</hi> God grant that our murmur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing (which never makes any thing better, but provokes a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and brings more rods and laſhes on the childe, and which God calls Rebellion, <hi>Numb.</hi> 16. 41, 46. with <hi>c.</hi> 17. 10.) do not either quite overturn us, or at leaſt protract eleven days journey into fourty years travel, as the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> murmuring did, <hi>Numb.</hi> 14. 26, 30. and cauſe that many of us ſhall fall in the Wilderneſs, and never ſee the good Land: Far be from me ſuch thoughts, ſuch praiſe <note n="b" place="margin">Adulator <hi>&amp;</hi> Laudator <hi>have both the ſame letters.</hi>
               </note>, or rather flattery, as to think or ſay, that the Grand Aſſembly (whereof You have ſo long, and with ſuch indefatigable pains, been the faithful Speaker) hath had no faults and errors (though I deſire ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:47130:3"/> to weep over them to God, then blaze them to men) re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membering often that ſtory of <hi>Gilbert Foliot,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> in <hi>H:</hi> 2. raign, <hi>Anno Chriſti</hi> 1161. who ſaith of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, that when he firſt entered into the Monastery, he zeal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly cryed out againſt the ſluggiſhneſs of his Governors; af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward, being choſen Governor, he inveighed againſt his ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periors; being choſen Prior, he cryed out againſt the Abbots; afterwards, being choſen Abbot, he excuſed them, and deep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly charged the Biſhops; but being choſen Biſhop, I began (ſaith he) to ſee how much eaſier it is to finde faults, then (when it is our own caſe) to mend them. I cannot ſay of your Honorable Senate, what that learned and holy <note n="c" place="margin">
                  <hi>Who was, as</hi> Nazian, <hi>ſaid of</hi> Baſil, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>Beza</hi> (who lived 86. years) ſaid of himſelf, that his Head never once aked; but truly I think a bad Stomack may make a good Head to ake, and our ſins and murmurings may much fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that which we ſo much complain againſt: <hi>Iſrael</hi> ſinned, and God left <hi>David</hi> to number the People, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 34. 1. and I verily beleeve that our good and wiſe God (that can bring light out of darkneſs, good out of evil, and extract medicines out of poyſons, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4. 6.) hath ſometimes brought much good to this Land, even out of Your Errors and our Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies; and hath many times (a Mercy that <hi>Luther</hi> much noted, and often bleſſed God for) not taken advantage of your and our failings to our deſtruction, but hereby made us more zealous, wary, and active afterwards. O the wiſdom and mercy of our gracious God! Of all the Saints in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, I finde no one that vented more impatience then <hi>Job,</hi> as Cap. 3. curſing, (though not God, as Satan promiſed, <hi>Job</hi> 1. 11. &amp; 2. 5. yet curſing,) <hi>Job</hi> 6. 8, 9. &amp; 7. 14, 15. &amp; 10. 18, 19. Yet the Holy Ghoſt, <hi>Jam.</hi> 5. 11. highly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mends <hi>Jobs</hi> patience, and lays it down for a pattern, never naming one word of his impatience. <hi>Abraham</hi> ſhewed much unbelief, twice thereby denying his wife, yet is chronicled for the Father of the <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 4. 11, 18, 19, 20.</note> faithful, and one ſtrong in Faith. <hi>Jeho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhaphat</hi> joyned friendſhip with <hi>Ahab,</hi> 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 18. 3. went with him to battel againſt <hi>Ramoth Gilead,</hi> Verſ. 27, 28. and after that he had been reproved for it by <hi>Jehu,</hi> 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 19. 2.
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:47130:4"/> yet he again makes friendſhip with <hi>Ahaziah,</hi> 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 20. 25. and marries his ſon to <hi>Ahabs</hi> daughter, 2 <hi>Chro.</hi> 21. 6. and yet the Lord ſaith of him, 1 <hi>King.</hi> 22. 43. that he turned not aſide from doing that which was right in the eyes of the Lord. How ſhould this melting patience cauſe you to bleſs and act for this gracious God, and to chronicle his mercies to poſterity! How often have I wiſhed, that Your Honor, who have had, during almoſt theſe ten years, ſo perfect information of all the wonders of our God to and for his People in this Nation, had <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 107. 43.</note> kept a perfect Diary thereof! or if You have ſo done, that You would communicate the ſame to the world, which would be one of the rareſt pieces of humane ſtories. How wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and various have been the goings of our God in this Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, theſe ten years, and ſtill are, like His dealing with His People of the Jews, after their return from <hi>Babylon! Zech.</hi> 14. 6, 7. It was for a long time neither day nor night, clear nor dark, (a man could not gueſs what a day it would be by the eye of ſenſe, but preſently after a Sun-ſhine, a Cloud;) and all this to ſhake off ſuch as live by ſenſe, and not by Faith, and ſerve themſelves of God and the Publique (as <hi>Jehu</hi> and <hi>Judas</hi> did;) and to let the Saints ſee, that things are carry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on <hi>not by might, nor by power, but by the Lord of hoaſts his own Spirit,</hi> Zech. 4. 6. nevertheleſs in the evening time it ſhall be light. And I am (in the midſt of a cloudy day) the more encouraged, when I conſider, 1. That the work is in the hand of a good and wiſe Maſter-builder, who ever the inſtruments be; In all theſe turnings there is a Spirit in the Wheels, and the Wheels are full of eyes, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 1. Secondly, God ſees and aims further then the beſt Agents and Instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments that are uſed in the work: The Apostles did not ſee, in the work themſelves were imployed in, ſo far as Christ meant, but he lets them ſee more and more by ſteps and degrees what he would have done, <hi>Mark</hi> 4. 28. So <hi>Ezek.</hi> 47. 3, 4. and God hath led us along with a Cloud and Fire, and owned us in the Mount, and midſt of ſtraits. Thirdly, The light of the Truth (I mean, not Satans deluſions, and mens phan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies, but true Light) much ſpreads in <hi>America, New-England,</hi>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:47130:4"/> in <hi>Wales,</hi> in the North, &amp;c. Poor Creatures flock like Doves to the windows, and the Kingdom of Heaven ſuffers vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence: And if it be ſaid, ſo do Profaneneſs and Hereſies ſpread; I anſwer, it was always ſo in times of Reformation, till things could be ſetled, Satan more ſtruggles; and when God is giving phyſick, the diſeaſe more breaks forth, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 7. 1. When did curſed Doctrines and Practices more break forth in the Old Teſtament, then in <hi>Malachi's</hi> time, when the Jews were returned from <hi>Babylon</hi> to reform Church and State in <hi>Canaan? Mal.</hi> 3. 14, 15. See <hi>Iſrael</hi> through the Wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. Fourthly, Compare former times impartially with theſe, we ſhall finde, thirteen, fourteen, or twenty years ago, traps of ſeveral kindes layd for conſciencious Miniſters and Chriſtians; men durſt not meet together to ſeek Gods face, humble their Souls; Sermons on Lords days in the afternoon, weekly Exerciſes, &amp;c. reſtrained, the very face of piety diſcountenanced, and they that wrought wickedneſs, and moſt zealous againſt Puritans, were exalted: dumb dogs, non-reſidents, ſports on Lords day, &amp;c. favoured: But how are godly men and godlineſs countenanced in good meaſure? what happy alteration in our <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſities for advance of piety, (though ſtill more is to be wiſhed?) And though too many Errors in ſome Members of our Armies, yet ſee heretofore every Town generally ſent ſuch out to be Souldiers, who were of the baſeſt ſort for drunkenneſs and villany, that knew no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing; compare our Army now with thoſe here formerly, and then judge without prejudice. Fifthly, Though mens <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ims were but little and ſtrait at firſt, as <hi>Luther</hi> ſaid, that when he firſt began, he meant no more, but to withſtand Popiſh <note n="a" place="margin">Occaſione <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>dinatio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>s indulgentiarum pretio numerato <hi>Lutherus</hi> initio fuit permotus ad hoc quod ſuſcepit Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mationis opus, &amp;c.</note> Pardons and ſelling of Indulgences; yet neither would God nor his Enemies let him alone, till he reſolved with <hi>Moſes</hi> not to leave a hoof, neither root nor branch of Popery: So God and our Enemies heighten Your ſpirits. Sixthly, We hear what God is ſtill working, in bringing in many poor Natives in <hi>America,</hi> (whether they be the Poſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the Jewiſh ten Tribes, as <hi>Peter Martyr</hi> of old, and <note n="b" place="margin">
                  <hi>Mr</hi> Thorow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>good.</note> o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of late give very probable conjectures, and if ſo, Mr
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:47130:5"/> 
               <hi>Brightman</hi> and others may well be owned for Prophets, who above fourty years ago foretold the Calling of the <hi>Jews</hi> to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin about the year 1650. or whether they be Gentiles) to embrace the Gospel with tears, prayers, marvelous zeal and Reformation: And how have we ſeen the finger of God all a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long, reſtraining the rage of men, letting the Enemy vent onely ſo much fury as might conduce to Gods praiſe! <hi>Pſal.</hi> 76. 10. He that ſtills the noiſe of the Seas, ſtills the tumules of the People, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 65. 7. The great God ſwaddles the mighty raging Ocean like a little Infant, (yea, more eaſily then any Midwiſe can do the leaſt childe) in ſwadling bands, <hi>Job</hi> 38. 9. and the Original word <note n="c" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> of <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Fraenum Capiſtrum.</hi>
               </note> uſed <hi>Mark</hi> 4. 39. for Chriſts ſtill<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the winds and Sea, ſignifies his putting a bridle in the mouth of the winds and Sea, whereby he turns them about (when moſt bluſtering and raging) more eaſily then any man can do the nimbleſt horſe: He gathers the winds in his fiſt, <hi>Pro.</hi> 30. 4. nods <note n="d" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> men to death, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 80. 16. with a blaſt, <hi>Job</hi> 4. 9. And how may all theſe experiments ſtir You up to truſt God for the future, and be ſincerely active for God againſt Your own and the Nations ſins and diſtempers! as <hi>Henricus Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceps</hi> when he fought againſt the Hungarians made this Vow to God, that if the Lord would give him a victory over his E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies, he would purge his Country from <note n="e" place="margin">
                  <hi>Commonly ſo called, elſe buying livings was not</hi> Simons <hi>ſin, Act.</hi> 8. 18, <hi>to</hi> 20. <hi>though uſually called</hi> Simony.</note> 
               <hi>Simony,</hi> which then much raigned therein. And I beſeech you return the praiſe and glory of all not to Your ſelves, or Armies, but to the free mercy and goodneſs of God alone. Pope <hi>Hadrian</hi> having built <note place="margin">
                  <hi>K.</hi> W. Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fus <hi>when two Monks came to him to buy an Abbots place, each outvying o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in great ſums of money for it, the K. asked a third Monk that ſtood by, what he would give, who anſwered, never a peny, for that its againſt my Conſcience (ſaid he) to give any thing; then ſaid the King, of all the three thou beſt deſerveſt it, and ſo beſtowed it upon him.</hi>
               </note> a ſumptuous Colledg at <hi>Lovain,</hi> cauſed this inſcription to be engraven upon it, <hi>Utrecht</hi> (where he was born) <hi>planted me, Lovain</hi> (where he had his education) <hi>watered me,</hi> and <hi>Caeſar</hi> (who promoted him to the Popedom) <hi>gave the increaſe,</hi> under which a witty Paſſenger ſubſcribed, <hi>Hic Deus nihil fecit,</hi> Here God did nothing. Nay, much rather ſay as <hi>Dan: Cra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merus, Nil ſcio, nil poſſum, nil ſum quoque quod tamen eſſe, ſeire &amp; poſſe aliquid dicor id omne Dei eſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:47130:5"/>
            <p> Or as holy <hi>Cruciger, Omnia praetereunt praeter amare Deum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now, Honorable Sir, give me leave to acquaint you with the Reaſons which moved me to preſume to preſent this plain Diſcourſe to Your Honor.</p>
            <p n="1">1. To give a poor, yet humble and hearty acknowledgment to the world, of the many favors and great undeſerved reſpect which I have received freely from you, and the kinde offers which you long ſince made to me, upon your firſt taking notice of me, as far above my deſerts as deſires, the embracing whereof my other Obligations would not permit. And ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, That ſeeing the love of this Common-wealth is deeply rooted in your heart, (deeper then the loſs of <hi>Callice</hi> in Queen <hi>Maries,</hi> or the love of his Country in <hi>A. Fulvius</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">Non Catilinae te genui ſed pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triae, <hi>ſaid</hi> Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus Fulvius, <hi>when he ſlew his own ſon with his own hands for Treaſon a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth.</hi>
               </note>) which pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique frame of ſpirit is a thing most highly commendable, though it be not true which <hi>Tully</hi> ſaith, <hi>Omnes qui patriam conſerverunt, adjuverunt, auxerunt, certum eſt eſſe in Coelo,)</hi> and that God hath called Your Honor to a very high place and work, (for ſuch work, and ſo long a time, as you have no preſident before you) let me hear (I beſeech you) take occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to become a humble Petitioner to your Honor, and by You to the Common-wealths Repreſentative, in a few parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars: It hath been my lot for ſome time to be conſtantly at <hi>York</hi> Aſſizes, (not as having any ſuit at all, but in attend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance to ſome worthy friends,) where my heart even bled with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in me, to ſee ſuch raſhneſs and careleſſneſs in ſwearing, too many offering to ſwear that (but that the Judges were more careful and honeſt) which after ſome diſcourſe they were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced to be untrue. Oh that there could be found ſome other way then ſwearing of every man at the Aſſizes, whether to puniſh falſe witneſſes by pecuniary or corporal mulct (as the new-converted Natives of <hi>America</hi> do puniſh the ſin of ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, for the firſt lye 5 <hi>s.</hi> for the ſecond 10 <hi>s.</hi> for the third 20 <hi>s.)</hi> or what other way ſhall ſeem to Your Wiſdoms moſt convenient; which perhaps would more reſtrain ſuch careleſs and conſcienceleſs perſons from unjuſt witneſs-bearing, then any their Oaths; ſo might the Land be much freed from the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:47130:6"/> burthen of Oaths under which it groans, <hi>Jerem.</hi> 23. 10. and from that flying roll, <hi>Zech.</hi> 5. 23. It is obſervable that the word in the Hebrew, which the Scripture uſeth for ſwear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, is always uſed in the paſſive <note n="a" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>juratus fuit.</hi>
               </note> voyce, to note (ſay ſome) that a man ſhould not ſwear but when an Oath is layd upon him, and he driven to it: the word alſo hath the ſignification of ſeven <note n="b" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>and</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note>, as having reference, ſay ſome, to the ſeven Spirits of God before the Throne, before whom we ſwear, and therefore ſhould ſwear in truth, righteouſneſs, and judgment, <hi>Jerem.</hi> 4. 2. <hi>Rev.</hi> 1. 4. <hi>&amp;</hi> 5. 6. and not raſhly, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 5. 2. How ſcrupulous and tender was good <hi>Eliezer,</hi> and how clear would he be ere he would ſwear? <hi>Gen.</hi> 34. 4, 5, 6. Such a mans word is worth more then many mens Oaths. When <hi>Lewis</hi> the French King was taken Priſoner by the <hi>Turks,</hi> and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter they agreed upon Articles, for confirming whereof the Sultan offered to ſwear, that if he broke any of the Articles, he would renounce his Mahomet, requiring K. <hi>Lewis</hi> to ſwear likewiſe, that if he broke any of his Articles, he would deny his Chriſt to be God; which Oath <hi>Lewis</hi> deteſting, and offering rather to dye then to take it, the Sultan wondering at his tenderneſs and conſtancy, took his word without any Oath at all, and ſo publiſhed the League: I complain not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt ſwearing as unlawful in it ſelf, nor yet againſt the manner uſed therein, in touching or kiſſing the book, (though that godly ſufferer <hi>William Thorp,</hi> and ſome other eminent Worthies in <hi>England,</hi> did mightily oppoſe this, and ſuffered much for their Opinion herein above 240 years ago, in the reign of our King <hi>Henry</hi> 4.) onely I could wiſh, if it were poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, this common and raſh ſwearing and for, wearing might be prevented.</p>
            <p n="2">2. I beſeech you further what in you lies, the ſuppreſſing of curſed Hereſies and Fandamental Errors, which are no ſmall <note n="c" place="margin">
                  <hi>See the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtle of the</hi> Walachtian <hi>Churches ſent to the Aſſembly of Divines at</hi> Weſtminſter, Quomodo omne geaus Haereſium in ultum permitti poſsit in illa Civitate quae tam expreſſo juramento ſeſe devinxit ad omnia Sciſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mata cy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>enda.</note> blemiſh to our endevored Reformation: It's more then three years ago ſince a forreign Pen wrote to our diſgrace in a Book
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:47130:6"/> publiſhed at <hi>Dantzick, Anglia his quatuor annis facta eſt col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luvies &amp; lerna omnia Errorum &amp; Sectarum, nulla a condito orbe Provincia, tam parvo ſpatio tot monſtroſas Haereſes pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tulit, atque haec; Epiſe porum tempora intra ſexaginta annos non niſi quatuor ſectas protulerunt, &amp; eas plerunque in obſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro latentes, &amp;c.</hi> I pray you help us really to confute his testi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony: I know when the Jews returned from <hi>Babylon</hi> to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form the Church and State, they ſet up firſt the Altar, then the Temple, then the walls of the City, (as if we would ſay, firſt Worſhip, then Doctrine, then Diſcipline,) but yet up the walls did go alſo at laſt: The Lord help you and us againſt this dangerous flood of the Dragon, which ſo hurts both broa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers and receivers. <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſaith of <hi>Arrius</hi> the Heretick, that his pains are increaſed in Hell, as oft as any one, through his Hereſie, is ſeduced from the Faith; and we finde it true, that the itch of Error, if not prevented, oft-times breaks forth into the ſcab of Atheiſm. We have publiquely hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled our ſelves in this Nation more then once for our Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies; I beſeech you act what you juſtly may againſt them: We hear what Laws our Brethren in <hi>New-England</hi> have made <note n="d" place="margin">
                  <hi>Mr</hi> Thorow-good.</note> about three years ago againſt <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> and others (not for their Conſcience, which they may keep to themſelves, but) for infecting and ſeducing others. And we read <note n="e" place="margin">
                  <hi>M.</hi> Weld <hi>riſe, growth, &amp;c.</hi>
               </note> that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout thirteen years ago, <hi>anno</hi> 1637. they convented at New-Town in <hi>New-England</hi> ſome of the principal Ring-leaders, and not onely publiquely admoniſhed and excommunicated, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo impriſoned, and after baniſhed them. <hi>Luther</hi> fore-told above one hundred years ago, that the Familiſtical Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors, which he then in their bud oppoſed, would hereafter riſe up, with more ſubtilty and danger, in the days of more light of the Gospel, and ſure now Satan is buſie in ſowing Tares.</p>
            <p n="3">3. I beſeech you encourage and further (as, bleſſed be God, you have begun a glorious work that way) a godly orthodox painful Miniſtry in <hi>England, Ireland, Wales, &amp;c.</hi> that God, that hath always payd ſo well for nurſing his children, and counted that done to him which is done to them, will not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matth.</hi> 25. <hi>Acts</hi> 9. <hi>Mat.</hi> 10. 40, 41 42. <hi>Zech.</hi> 2. 8,</note> any pains and care for his faithful Miniſters, and propa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gating his Gospel, advancing piety and learning with all due
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:47130:7"/> and needful encouragements thereto: Satan every way op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſeth them, and Gods work by them: <hi>Elijah</hi> was called the <hi>Troubler of Iſrael,</hi> 1 King. 18. 17. <hi>Amos</hi> charged for con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spiracy, <hi>Amos</hi> 7. 10. <hi>Paul</hi> counted a <note n="f" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> peſtilent fellow, (a very poſt) a mover of Sedition, and Ring-leader of a Sect, <hi>Acts</hi> 24. 5. and Chriſt himſelf a Teacher of New Doctrines, <hi>Mark</hi> 1. 27. as well as <hi>Paul,</hi> Acts 17. 9. <note n="g" place="margin">Jeremy <hi>was layd by the heels for a Traytor to the State,</hi> Luther <hi>called a trum<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pet of rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and</hi> Beza <hi>a ſeedſman of ſedition.</hi> Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum crimen eo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum qui crimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne vacabant, <hi>as</hi> Lipſius <hi>out of</hi> Tacitus.</note> Therefore they ſtand in more need of your further encouragement; ſo ſhall you be not titulary, but real defenders of the Faith. The Pope ſent over to <hi>James</hi> the fourth King of <hi>Scotland</hi> a Sword with this Title, <hi>Protector of the Faith:</hi> and preſently after another Sword to our King <hi>Henry</hi> the eighth with this Title, <hi>Defender of the Faith;</hi> but the meaning was, to protect the Popiſh Faith, and not Chriſts pure Gospel; and accordingly both thoſe Kings afterwards cauſed ſeveral godly men to be burned for the Truth in their Dominions, and great ignorance followed, men wholly ſtudying Popiſh fancies, and neglecting Gods Word, ſo as <hi>George Creichton</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Dunkel</hi> confeſſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed that he had lived Biſhop many years, yet never knew any thing of the Old and New Testament.</p>
            <p n="4">4. I beſeech you, while you ſit in that Honorable Senate, forget not poor Priſoners in the Gaol, but let there be in every County ſome proviſion made for their Souls, ſo that they may not be made in their Priſons ten times more the children of Hell, then before, and moſt unfit to dye, when moſt unable to live. How much good did that learned and holy Mr <hi>Perkins</hi> that way in his time! One Malefactor (amongst others) crying out upon the Ladder to Mr <hi>Perkins,</hi> that he feared <note place="margin">Non metuo mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri, ſed damnari.</note> not Death, but a worſe thing, was even melted into tears at Mr <hi>Perkins</hi> his Prayer, and dyed joyfully. What a bleſſed work would this be, to provide ſome able man (and means for him) to preach to, and catechiſe theſe poor Souls, that ſo they may not be in bondage to Satan, but Chriſts free men, that when the Juſtice of the Law will not ſuffer them to live, the Mercy in the Gospel may fit them for death. A reuerend Miniſter of this Nation (now with God) ſaid that one ſhilling a quarter of every pariſh (one with another) in the County of <hi>Somerſet</hi> (which is no burthen to any man) would encour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:47130:7"/> ſome godly man to this work; ſo might we perhaps, through Gods mercy, ſee more penitent theeves.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Contribute (I beſeech you) your beſt skill and help for the joynting of godly and faithful men, who agree in the ſame Fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damentals of Doctrine, and truth of practice towards God and the State, and ſhall agree in the ſame Heaven at night: <hi>Tragediae Lutheranae mihi ipſi etiam calculo ſunt moleſtiores,</hi> (ſaid <hi>Eraſmus;)</hi> The Differences among godly men more troubled <hi>Eraſmus</hi> then the ſtone: It's a thouſand pities to ſee what ſtrangeneſs in Opinion, Affection, and Converſation a few years of peace have bred in too many, who agreed, mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and wept together in times of Trouble, (like ſheep run of a heap in a ſtorm, but ſpread up and down the mountain in a Sun-ſhine.) How do the <hi>Philiſtins</hi> hereupon triumph, publiſh it in Gath, and raiſe up their hopes! And I fear there are ſome curſed ſpirits that do purpoſely heighten our Diviſions, to ruine us both. I have often ſadly thought of that paſſage of <hi>Oecolampadius</hi> to the <hi>Lutherans,</hi> when the fire of conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion grew hot 'twixt the <hi>Zuinglians</hi> and them (as they were called,) and the ſubtil <hi>Jeſuites</hi> and <hi>Papiſts</hi> joyned themſelves with the <hi>Lutherans</hi> in the Sacramentary quarrel, and ſtroked them on the head <hi>(eos laudabant, &amp; in pretio habebant, &amp;c.)</hi> purpoſely to make the breach wider and irreconcileable, to ruine both; <hi>Error condonari poteſt</hi> (ſaith <hi>Oecolamp.) diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordiam neque ſi ſanguinem fundamus expiabimus:</hi> and as our Diviſions bring ſcandal, ſo danger (as <hi>Machiavils</hi> rule was) by being divided <hi>in minutula fruſtula. Cambden</hi> obſerves that the low Countries ſuspecting the friendſhip of the Engliſh <hi>(anno</hi> 1587.) ſtamped money with two Earthen Pitchers ſwimming on the Sea, with this Motto, <hi>Si collidimur, fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gimur;</hi> If we daſh one againſt another, we are both broken. I wiſh that <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Holland, England</hi> and <hi>Scotland, Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> and <hi>England,</hi> would timely conſider this, whom to cement and glue firmly, was worth the ſtudy and labour of another <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the great, nay, of an <hi>Engliſh Parliament;</hi> but lieth onely in the Power of the Almighty. In the Raign of <hi>Henry</hi> the eight <hi>(anno 1536.)</hi> fourty thouſand <hi>Yorkſhire</hi> men roſe up in Arms, to uphold the Popes authority, their
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:47130:8"/> old Traditions, Latine Service, (though alaſs whether it was curſing or praying they knew not,) their Beads, Croſſes, and other Church-ornaments (as they called them,) which they thought <hi>Cromwel</hi> would then have pulled down: This Riſing they called the <hi>Holy Pilgrimage,</hi> on their Colours they had the five wounds of Chriſt, with the letters <hi>JESUS</hi> in the midſt: The King ſent down a great Army againſt them, both Armies drew neer to one another, the place, day, and hour of battel was ſet, but that night, before the battel ſhould be, fell a ſmall rain, which ſo raiſed a little brook that was betwixt the Armies, that neither Army could come at the other all the next day, the neighboring Inhabitants having never ſeen that brook ſwell neer that height, (which the day before a man might have gone over dry-ſhod,) though they had often ſeen far greater rain: both Armies looked at it as Gods mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raculous hand, forbidding their fighting, and ſo treated, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed, and departed quietly: How happily was the effuſion of blood prevented? Alaſs, how do we ſee ſincere godly men rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy (through different apprehenſions and remnant of corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) like <hi>Abraham</hi> and <hi>Lot, Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas,</hi> to fall out! In Queen <hi>Maries</hi> days of perſecution, ſome godly men (after Martyrs) thought that they might not with a ſafe conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence fly away, though they had fair warning and opportunity, as <hi>Latimer, Taylor, B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>adford, &amp;c.</hi> but were bound to tarry and witneſs the truth of God: Others (though very godly) thought they might not with a good Conſcience ſtay, but ſhould be wilfully acc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſſary to their own death, as <hi>Fox, Juel, Knox, &amp;c.</hi> and when thoſe godly men that fled did re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn, ſome approved Church Government by Biſhops, others could not: ſome conformed to the Ceremonies eſtabliſhed, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers durſt not; yet many of both Opinions agreed in Grace and Glory: Yea, even Biſhop <hi>Andrews</hi> could ſay in his E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtle to <hi>P. Moulin</hi> concerning thoſe Churches that had not Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, nor owned that Government, <hi>Ferreus ſit qui ſalutem eis neget, nos non <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>mus ill<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ferrei:</hi> and yet alas in matters of ſmal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler moment <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ud<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>um partium is magna pars ſtudiorum:</hi> You may (through Gods bleſſing) much conduce to a happy union, however God will reward you <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>and not</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>:
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:47130:8"/> What a journey took <hi>Polycarp (anno Chriſti</hi> 157.) to recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cile that frivolous brabble 'twixt <hi>Romans</hi> and <hi>Aſians</hi> about keeping <hi>Eaſter? Where ſtrife and contention is, there is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion and every evil work,</hi> Jam. 3. 16. But <hi>where godly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity and unity amongſt brethren, there the Lord commands his bleſſing, and life for evermore,</hi> Pſal. 133. Let me call to minde one remarkable victory to this purpoſe; About ninety years ago, when <hi>Mary</hi> Queen of <hi>Scots</hi> (Widow to <hi>James</hi> the fifth King of <hi>Scotland,</hi> and Grandmother to King <hi>James</hi> of Great <hi>Britain)</hi> would have forcibly eſtabliſhed Popery in <hi>Scotland,</hi> and had ſecretly received divers <hi>French</hi> into <hi>Leith</hi> for that end, and garriſoned that place with them, ſhe was op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed by the Proteſtants in <hi>Scotland,</hi> who being too weak, prevailed with Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> to ayd them; ſhe ſent over the Duke of <hi>Norfolk</hi> with an Army to aſſiſt the <hi>Scots,</hi> the <hi>Engliſh</hi> with the <hi>Scottiſh Proteſtants</hi> layd ſiege to <hi>Leith,</hi> from whence the <hi>French</hi> and the Queens Popiſh party of <hi>Scots</hi> ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lied out, and ſlew divers both <hi>Engliſh</hi> and <hi>Scotch,</hi> and layd their dead bodies naked upon the top of their Works in the hot moneth of <hi>June (anno</hi> 1560.) againſt the Sun: The Queen of <hi>Scots</hi> looked out of her window upon the Dead Bodies, and ſaid, <q>
                  <hi>Yonder is the goodlieſt Tapeſtry that ever my eyes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>held, I would the whole fields hereabouts were ſtrawed with the ſame ſtuff:</hi>
               </q> After which words ſhe ſhortly fell ſick and dyed; and the Popiſh party beſieged in <hi>Leith</hi> were forced to yeeld and depart; <hi>Scotland</hi> was quieted, and the Truth of Religion hereby there eſtabliſhed: but ere our Army return<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed home, it was deſired that there might be a ſolemn Day of Thanksgiving to <hi>God</hi> kept at <hi>Giles's</hi> Church in <hi>Edinburgh in July,</hi> 1560. where one prayer was then ſolemnly put up to Heaven, and recorded in <hi>Scotland, in perpetuam <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ei memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riam;</hi> part whereof was in theſe words: <q>
                  <hi>O Lord whereas thou haſt made our Confederates of England inſtruments to ſet us at this liberty, and to whom in thy Name we have promiſed mutual faith again, let us never fall into that un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kindneſs O Lord, that either we declare our ſelves unthank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to them, or Profaners of thy holy Name, but confound O Lord the counſels of thoſe that go about to break that</hi>
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:47130:9"/> 
                  <hi>moſt godly League contracted in thy name, and retain thou us ſo firmly together by thy holy Spirit, that Satan never have any power to ſet us again at variance or diſcord.</hi>
               </q> I add no more, but <hi>fiat,</hi> Amen and Amen, &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="6">6. As I heartily beg of <hi>God</hi> for you and us, that never any iniquity may be establiſhed by a Law, ſo would I beg that our Laws may be ſo framed according to <hi>Gods holy Word</hi> (ſuit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able wherto ſomething is begun <note n="h" place="margin">
                  <hi>I leave it to Your Honors to judg whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther one Poſt in a weeke which needs not travel on the Lords day at all (when no Caſe of neceſſity, or</hi> extraordinary,) <hi>was not better, then two, who travel every Lords day, all the day con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtantly.</hi>
               </note> for <hi>Lords-Day,</hi> and againſt <hi>Adultery, Inceſt, Swearing,</hi> &amp;c.) as might cauſe our Lawyers and others more to read and ſtudy the Scriptures, therein to know more fully and clearly the Law of our <hi>Land,</hi> as <hi>Eleuthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius</hi> long ſince wrote to K. <hi>Lucius:</hi> but herein I ſubmit (as is meet) to Your and the honorable Senates grave and wiſe Judgments, humbly craving your pardon for this tediouſneſs and bold <hi>Dedication.</hi> I ſhall not fail, right honorable Sir, to bow my knees unto the God and Father of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, for you, and the Heads of our Tribes, that our onely wiſe and good God would give you a true ſight of, and repent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance for what is amiſs, (for I know you are far from <note n="i" place="margin">
                  <hi>Biſhop of</hi> Lichfield <hi>and</hi> Coventry.</note> Biſhop <hi>Overton</hi> his minde, who accuſed a faithful Miniſter <note n="k" place="margin">
                  <hi>Mr</hi> Hugh Clark <hi>Vicar of</hi> Woolston <hi>in</hi> Warwickshire.</note> within his Dioceſs of Treaſon, and committed him to <hi>Warwick</hi> Gaol for praying before his Sermon for Queen <hi>Elizabeth, That God would forgive her her ſins.</hi> You are not ſuch ſtrangers to your own hearts and actions, as Cardinal <hi>Bellarmine,</hi> who could not finde any ſin to confeſs, ſave one or two in his youth.) I ſhall lap you round about in my poor prayers, that God would more and more diſcover unto you his minde and work, make you all ſpiritual Princes to Jeſus Chriſt, guide, bleſs, and carry you through in Gods work, and for the Publique, in ſuch a manner, as you may not onely do his work, but have a ſhare and comfort in it. I add no more but Doctor <hi>Hollands</hi> Farewel, which he uſed when he took his leave of the Fellows of <hi>Exeter</hi> Colledg in <hi>Oxford,</hi> where he was Principal, <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendo te dilectioni Dei, &amp; odio Papatus omniſque ſuperſtiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onis,</hi> and humbly and heartily ſubſcribe my ſelf</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Honors moſt obliged and faithful Servant in the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of God and the Publique, <hi>JOHN SHAWE.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:47130:9"/>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:47130:10"/>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:47130:10"/>
            <head>The Princes Royal: OR A Sermon preached at the Min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter in YORK on the Lords-Day morning in the Aſſize week, March 24. 1650. Upon that Text,</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>PSALM 45. Verſ. 16.</bibl>
               <q>In ſtead of thy fathers ſhall be thy children, whom thou mayſt make Princes in all the Earth.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>FOr the matter of this <hi>Pſalm,</hi> it is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> a Song of Loves; for the end of it, it is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> to inſtruct, ſaith the title of this <hi>Pſalm:</hi> Some think <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſalmorum liber, quaecun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que utilia ſunt ex omnibus continet,</hi> ſaid <hi>Baſil,</hi> and ſo <hi>Auguſtin,</hi> The Book of the <hi>Pſalms</hi> is a ſtore-houſe of all holy Truths in other books ſeverally diſperſed.</note> the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> which ſignifieth <hi>lillies,</hi> points out the matter of the <hi>Pſalm, viz.</hi> the love 'twixt Chriſt and his Church, who both are compared to <hi>lillies, Cant.</hi> 2. 1, 2.</p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:47130:11"/>
            <p> At marriages (eſpecially of great perſons) they uſed to have Epithalamial ſongs ſung, the principal matter whereof was the commendation of the Bridegroom and the Bride: ſuitable hereto the Holy Ghoſt endites (whoſoever was the pen-man) a divine Epithalamial <hi>Pſalm,</hi> relating to, and ſetting forth, nextly and immediately in the letter and ſhadow, the praiſes of <hi>Solomon</hi> and his wife (the daughter of <hi>Pharaoh</hi> King of <hi>Egypt;)</hi> for though <hi>Solomon</hi> had ſeven hundred wives, and three hundred Concubines, 1 <hi>King.</hi> 11. 3. yet did he eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally affect <hi>Pharaohs</hi> daughter, 1 <hi>King.</hi> 3. 1. The Jewiſh Rabbies ſay, that one of the Articles in the agreement of mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage 'twixt <hi>Solomon</hi> and <hi>Pharaohs</hi> daughter was, that ſhe ſhould forſake her Idolatry and blinde Superſtition of <hi>Egypt,</hi> and embrace the Worſhip and Service of the true God; which Article ſeems to be alluded to here, <hi>Verſ.</hi> 10. 11. but under the ſimilitude of <hi>Solomons</hi> marriage with <hi>Pharaohs</hi> daughter is ultimately, principally and myſtically ſet out the Lord Chriſt his marriage with the Church (as it is alſo in the Book of <hi>Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles;)</hi> and even ſome of the learneder Jews are forced to confeſs, that many things in this <hi>Pſalm</hi> cannot be meant of <hi>Solomon</hi> and his Spouſe, but of the <hi>Meſſiah</hi> and his Church, as <hi>verſ.</hi> 1. he ſpeaks of the things touching the King but that King is God, whoſe throne endures for ever, <hi>Verſ.</hi> 6. So <hi>Verſ.</hi> 11. 18. and for the Spouſe, ſhe is ſuch a one whoſe chief glory lies within, <hi>Verſ.</hi> 13. And for their Children, though <hi>Solomon</hi> had a thouſand Wives and Concubines, yet we read but of one ſon (whereas others who had but one wife, had many ſons;) and though <hi>Solomon</hi> was the wiſeſt of all meer mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tals ſince the Fall, yet his ſon <hi>Rehoboam</hi> very fooliſh; ſo that my Text cannot in the letter be meant of <hi>Solomon,</hi> who had not children whom he might make Princes in all Lands; nay, the Kingdom ever went leſs, after <hi>Solomons</hi> time: But to put all out of queſtion, the Holy Ghoſt applies this <hi>Pſalm</hi> to Chriſt and the Church, <hi>Heb.</hi> 1. 8, 9, &amp;c. So that this <hi>Pſalm</hi> is a continued Allegory (if not Type,) ſetting out, under the ſimilitude of <hi>Solomons</hi> marriage, the neer and happy union and dear affection 'twixt Chriſts and all Beleevers, and thoſe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:47130:11"/> children and choyce poſterity that Chriſt begets in his Church by his Spirit and Word: And here is, Firſt, the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation of the Bridegroom, from <hi>Verſ.</hi> 1. <hi>to</hi> 10. for his beauty, eloquence, and art, in ſoul-winning, juſtice and meek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, the glory of his garments, and palace, &amp;c. And then the commendation of the Bride, <hi>Verſ.</hi> 10. <hi>to</hi> 15. and of the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren converted and born again to Chriſt in the Church, <hi>Verſ.</hi> 16. <hi>Who ſhall be Princes in all Lands.</hi> Here then we have 1. implied, A ſpiritual marriage 'twixt Chriſt and the Church. 2. Their ſpiritual children and poſterity. 3. The royal dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of theſe children that are converted and born to Chriſt in the Church: <hi>they are Princes.]</hi> 4. The extent, in all Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, places of the Earth, where ever they dwell, though in poor Cottages, wandering in ſheep skins and goat skins, ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing down with poor fare, yet are they Princes in all the Earth. 5. See the great honor that redounds to the Church hereby, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Domus mea a me incipiet, tua vero in te deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net,</hi> ſaid <hi>Tully</hi> to the braging and prod<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>gal Roman.</note> whereas uſually men brag and glory of their ancient pedigree, moth-eaten antiquity, (though the Heathen Poet could ſay, where that goes alone, it's a poor commendation, <hi>Et quae non fecimus ipſi, vix ea nostra voco;)</hi> yet men glory of their Anceſtors and Families, that they are ſprung <hi>ab atavis regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus:</hi> The Holy Ghoſt ſaith, that this is a far greater honor, to have precious Converts dayly born to God, then all temporal pedigrees. <hi>[In ſtead of thy Fathers ſhall be thy chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The firſt Point (which is couched in the Text, and runs through the whole <hi>Pſalm,</hi> I ſhall onely point at <hi>in tranſitu,</hi> and ſo paſs to the next) is this, That there is a ſpiritual, glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and happy marriage 'twixt Chriſt and his Church: This is clear in all the Book of <hi>Canticles, Epheſ.</hi> 5. <hi>Iſai.</hi> 54. 5. <hi>Rev.</hi> 19. 7. <hi>&amp;</hi> 21. 9.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu.</hi> Wherein doth this ſpiritual myſtical marriage conſiſt?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> 1. <hi>Ex parte Sponſi,</hi> on the Bridegrooms part; who, 1. makes his choyce, and ſets his heart on whom he will: A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt men we ſay, that before marriage a man ſhould ſuit his choyce to his minde <hi>(viz.</hi> rightly regulated,) but after, his mind to his choyce, if ever he meant to have content or comfort in it: And
<gap reason="missing" extent="2 pages">
                  <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:47130:12"/> madneſs, and life tedious, without <hi>Christ: Nihil mihi ſapit, in quo non ſapit</hi> Jeſus Chriſt: A poor Soul loves to ſpeak to him, to hear him, and hear from him, loves his Word, ways, people, all that ſavors of <hi>Christ;</hi> loves nothing further then as it comes from, or tends to, or ſuits with, Jeſus Chriſt, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2. 2.</p>
            <p>4. She deſires never to part: No; the Soul doth not mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Chriſt till death them depart, or till God ſhall ſeparate them by death, but takes him for life, death, ever: The Soul never repenteth of this match, ſave onely that he was married no ſooner, and counts all his time loſt till then; as one born out of due time, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. 8.</p>
            <p>5. The Spouſe goeth to Chriſt the Husband for every thing: ſhe depends upon him; upon, 1. His Judgment, for counſel and direction what to do in all caſes. 2. Upon His Eye (and not mens eyes) for approbation of all we do to God or men. 3. Upon his Purſe, for maintenance and dayly ſupply in every grace and duty, &amp;c. The Wife loſeth her own name, and is called after her Husband; So <hi>it's no more I</hi> (ſaith <hi>Paul) but Christ in me, Gal.</hi> 2. 20.</p>
            <p>But I promiſed brevity herein, and therefore I ſhall onely give a ſhort touch by way of Application: And firſt, here is a <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe, </seg>1</label> ground of marvelous Comfort and Encouragement to all Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leevers, and that in divers caſes: As,</p>
            <p n="1">1. Againſt ſin (the worſt of evils;) Chriſt the Husband muſt pay the debt: <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>xori lis non intenditur,</hi> ſaith the Civil Law; If a poor woman marry a Prince to whom ſhe owed 10000 <hi>l.</hi> he may pay himſelf.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Fear not final falling away: <hi>Christ</hi> repents not of the match; he fore-knew, ere he married us, what we were, and would be: If any fall would now break it, it would have pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented it: A true Beleever may fail and fall; but, 1. It's but a particular guilt; he is guilty as to that fact: That thing that <hi>David</hi> did di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>pleaſed the Lord, but not a general guilt; his eſtate is good, and approved of God; his general courſe and frame of heart is holy. 2. It's but the guilt of a Childe, not an Enemy; we may provoke a Fathers diſpleaſure,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:47130:12"/> 
               <hi>Exod.</hi> 4. 14. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 106. 32. but it's not the wrath of a Judg to a Malefactor, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. 1. ſo as to caſt him out for ever, <hi>Joh.</hi> 8. 35.</p>
            <p n="3">3. We may go boldly to <hi>Christ</hi> our Husband at all times, both in Life, for counſel, direction, ſupply; and in Death <note n="a" place="margin">Death in it ſelf is the King of ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors, <hi>Iob</hi> 18. 14 <hi>Sigiſmund</hi> the Emperor, and <hi>Lewis</hi> the 11. king of <hi>France</hi> charged all their ſervants about them, that all the time of their ſickneſs they ſhould not dare to name in their Hearing that terrible word <hi>Death,</hi> How did the fear of <hi>Death</hi> keep the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e great men in a continual bondage? but fear not to go down to the grave, <hi>Gen.</hi> 46. 3 for thy Husband hath gone and ſweetened the way.</note>, becauſe death cannot break this match; and after death, at Judgment, becauſe when the world is on flaming fire, our Husband is our Judg: at death we go but to our Husband, to his Father, and our Father, <hi>Joh.</hi> 20. 17, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 54. 5. <hi>Tol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litur mors non né ſit, ſed né obſit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. This is a great honor to the Saints, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 149. 9. to be a Kings Spouſe: <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>xor fulget radiis mariti;</hi> If a woman marry with a Knight, ſhe is a Lady; if with an Earl, ſhe is a Counteſs; if with a King, ſhe is a Queen. If poor <hi>Ruth</hi> marry <hi>Boaz,</hi> ſhe is Lady of <hi>Bhthlehem-Judah:</hi> If <hi>Esther</hi> with <hi>Ahaſhuerus,</hi> ſhe is a Queen of vaſt dominions.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Comfort to us againſt many Croſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s and Afflictions here: A wife that hath many croſſes, yet this bears up her heart, I thank God I have a loving and kinde Husband: Or if ſhe hath but a bad Husband on Earth, yet, I have a kinde, tender, rich Husband in Heaven. It's ſaid of <hi>Rubenius Celer</hi> when he was dying, being asked what Motto he would have on his Grave-ſtone, he anſwered, onely this, That <hi>I have lived with my Wife fourty three years and eight moneths, and to this hour we never once fell out.</hi> Mr <hi>Fox</hi> in the Book of <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs</hi> tells of a godly man who lived at <hi>Clarkennel</hi> in the days of Queen <hi>Mary,</hi> who was marvelous tender over, and loving and kinde to his wife, yet ſhe accuſed him to the Popiſh Prieſts, whereupon he was apprehended, for ſpeaking againſt Popery in his Family; and after he was through Gods mercy deliver<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d, ſhe did a ſecond time accuſe him, that he would not go to the Maſs, and that he ſpoke againſt the Pope and
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:47130:13"/> their Idolatry, whereupon he was again apprehended, impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned, <note place="margin">This Aſſizes was a man condemned for poyſoning a loving wife.</note> in the Stocks in <hi>Lollards</hi> Tower, cruelly uſed, firſt one arm and leg in the Stocks, and then another, and his childe whipt to death, and after the woman went mad; but <hi>Chriſt</hi> is a marvelous kinde and tender Husband.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Fear not want, if marryed to <hi>Chriſt,</hi> the Heir of all, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 1. 3. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 23. 1. for with him came all things elſe, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. 32.<hi>—Deus meus &amp; omnia.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſecond <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe of Exhortation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. Entertain no Suitors now thou art marryed, no adulter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe. </seg>2</label> love; cut off right hand, foot, eye. When a woman is <note place="margin">Therefore the Husband call<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>the covering of her eyes, Gen.</hi> 20. 16. Iſai. 30. 22.</note> marryed ſhe now entertains no more Suitors, but quiets her heart in her Husband: So ſay we to all theſe curſed tempting luſts, I am now marryed, away, begone; <hi>Ego non ſum ego.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Long for <hi>Christ,</hi> if abſent: How do Wives long for their Husbands return, though poor ſinful men? ſo you, breathe after <hi>Christ</hi> in Heaven; ſee the Church, <hi>Cant.</hi> 5. How wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>com is he that brings news to a Mariners Wife? <hi>We espy your Huſband coming yonder, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Obey <hi>Christ,</hi> not as a Slave, but as a Wife, from a prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple of love: It's true in Gods eyes, <hi>quod cor non facit, non fit,</hi> If no love, no life: But obey <hi>Christ</hi> as a Wife; 1. In one place as well as another. 2. From and with the heart, <hi>Rom.</hi> 6. 17. 3. For Conſcience ſake to Gods Ordinance; Say to Satan, I am not mine own, I will ask my Husband. 4. Submit thy minde and will to <hi>Chriſts</hi> Judgment and Will: Thou thinkeſt this or that beſt, but he is onely wiſe, take his advice.</p>
            <p n="4">4. If <hi>Christ</hi> ſuffer in any of his ſervants, pity and help them: When King <hi>Edward</hi> was ſhot with an envenomed Dart, his Queen ſuck'd out the poyſon with her mouth, when no other way was found to cure him.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Bleſs <hi>Christ,</hi> and thank him, that would vouchſafe to <note place="margin">1 Sam. 25. 41. See <hi>Abigails</hi> deep comple<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment.</note> ſue to, or match with thee, whom he might have made a fire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brand, who hadſt ſaid him nay often.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Forſake all for him: <hi>Rebecca</hi> will leave Father, Mother,
<pb facs="tcp:47130:13"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:47130:14"/>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:47130:14"/> all, to go to <hi>Iſaac,</hi> and <hi>Rachel,</hi> for <hi>Jacob</hi> leaves <hi>Laban,</hi> and her Countrey, &amp;c. <hi>Gen.</hi> 2. 24.</p>
            <p>The 3. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> is for triall; art thou married to Chriſt? <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Doeſt thou know him with a taſting experimentall knowledge? <hi>Phil.</hi> 3. 9. ſhe is but a light huſwife who will caſt her ſelf on any whom ſhe knowes not. 2. Doeſt thou love his perſon, and not his portion onely? Doeſt thou love him for himſelf? 3. Doeſt thou love him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove all others? long for him when abſent? 4. Art thou ſorry that thou didſt put him off long? ſay him nay, ſo often? 5. As Chriſt bought and paid for thee more then thou art worth, ſo he changeth thee when married; <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> married an Ethiopian, and ſhe continued her hue when married; <hi>David</hi> bought <hi>Sauls</hi> daughter, and paid more then ſhe was worth, ſhe continued ſurly, but Chriſt changeth thoſe whom he marries, new hearts, new lives, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 36. 26. Holy Mr. <hi>Dod</hi> being asked, why he (preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to ſome Gentlewomen that uſed naked <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Tertullian</hi> would have called theſe, <hi>Pudor oſtenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titiae Virgini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatis:</hi> How may the Americans ſhame us, for there the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Indians in New-England ſince the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell came to them, have made a Law, that every one that goeth with naked breaſts ſhall pay five ſhillings.</note> breaſts, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ain dreſſe, &amp;c.) did no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſharply reprove them for it, and perſwade them to leave them? he anſwered, I will firſt labour to get Chriſt into their hearts, and then they will eaſily and quickly leave theſe of themſelves. 6. If married thou haſt loſt thy own name, ſo do Virgins when marry, and are called after their husband; ſo <hi>Paul,</hi> not I, but Chriſt in me, <hi>Gal.</hi> 2. 20. I go not out in my name, in my ſtrength, for my ends; but as the ancient Martyr ſaid, my name, ends, hopes, wayes, are all called Chriſtian.</p>
            <p>All thoſe thoſe who are borne again of Chriſt, they <note place="margin">2. <hi>Obſerv.</hi>
               </note> are Princes, whether they dwell in all the earth, in any County, City Town or Village, ſo many godly men there, ſo many Princes there, <hi>Rev.</hi> 1. 6. <hi>He hath made us Kings and Priests to God and his Father,</hi> &amp;c. Rev. 5. 10. <hi>And hath made us unto our God Kings and Priests, and we ſhall reigne on the earth.</hi> 1 Pet. 2. 9. <hi>But ye are a choſen genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>a Kingdom of Prieſts,</hi> Exo. 19. 6. The righteous are Kings, many righteous men, ſaith <hi>Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thew,</hi>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:47130:15"/> c. 13. 17. many Kings have deſired, &amp;c. ſaith <hi>Luke</hi> c. 10. 24.</p>
            <p>There are two things, which I would do, ere I can clearly apply it: 1. Shew you what kind of Princes all the people of God are. 2. Wherein their Princeſhip (or Kingſhip) conſiſts.</p>
            <p>1. Godly men (as ſuch) are not temporall, but ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall Princes; as Chriſt's, ſo their Kingdom is not of this world, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2. 6, 8. True it is, that godly men, as <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid,</hi> &amp;c. may be temporall Princes, but not <hi>Quatenus</hi> god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly men and Chriſts ſeed: And we had need to clear this, for great temporall Monarchs are very fearfull of any claime to their Kingdomes, or medling with their Titles. Our Chronicles mention one <hi>Burdet,</hi> a Merchant of Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, dwelling at the ſign of the Crown in Cheapſide in the dayes of our King <hi>Edward</hi> the fourth, <hi>Anno,</hi> 1483. who jeſtingly ſaid to his Son, that he would leave him heire to the Crown, meaning the ſign of the Crowne where he lived, for which he was apprehended, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in four hours hanged, drawne, and quartered for ſo ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: Kings love not that men ſhould <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pulcheria</hi> the vertuous and diſcreet ſiſter of <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doſius</hi> the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, ſeeing her brother the Emperor to ſigne many writings with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out reading them, cauſed a writing drawn and tendered, wherein he conſigned into her hands his wife <hi>Eudoxia,</hi> (formerly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Baptiſme call'd <hi>Athenais</hi> a poor woman, daughter of <hi>Leontig,</hi> who ſeeking at the Court for Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice in a pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate cauſe, took the Emperors affections, was baptized and married him) <hi>Eudoxia</hi> ſaid, it was too great a game to jeſt and play upon Diadems, though the good Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror much re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>formed by it.</note> jeſt with their Crowns; how fearfully ſtartled was <hi>Herod,</hi> when he heard tell of ſome Wiſemen asking for one that was borne King of the Jewes! <hi>Mat.</hi> 2. 1, 2, 3, indeed worſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid then hurt: the Saints are not by vertue of their birth from Chriſt temporall, but ſpirituall Kings, though car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall men mens ſlander is very common, that Gods people rebell and aime only to be temporall Kings, <hi>Nehem.</hi> 6. 6, 7. But know, that it's far better to be a ſpirituall Prince with God, then meerly a temporall Prince over men: Which will appear, 1. Becauſe the greateſt Kings on earth have uſually more croſſes on earth, then externall comforts; there is a great vanity in the chiefeſt perſon and places on earth, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 62. 9. The world hath now ſtood above 5000. years, and the greater half of this time was ſpent ere the Jewes had any ſetled King; at laſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the year of the world, 3761, God gave them a
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:47130:15"/> King, <hi>Saul</hi> by name, and there were but three Kings that governed and ruled over all the twelve Tribes, <hi>viz. Saul, David,</hi> and <hi>Solomon,</hi> and one of theſe <hi>(viz. Saul)</hi> came to a violent death, ſlew himſelfe, though perhaps the Amalekite helped to diſpatch him <note n="*" place="margin">If ſo, then <hi>Saul</hi> who had been cruell to <hi>David,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> cruell to him ſelf, and he that ſpared the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>malekites, and never proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red after, is at laſt ſlain by an Amalckite. 1 Sam. 15. 14 23. See <hi>Lightf<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> on that place <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> is onely uſed it. 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 1. 9. and ſignifies both <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> &amp; <hi>tremor vel arguſtre.</hi>
               </note> when his coat of male ſomewhat hidered his own ſpear from making that ſpeedy end which he deſired, as the words in the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew may be read, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 1. 9. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> After theſe three Kings deaths, the twelve Tribes were divided into two Kingdoms, two Tribes clave to <hi>Rehoboam Solomons</hi> Son and H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>, and made up the Kingdom of Judah; and ten Tribes to <hi>J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>oboam. Solomons</hi> Servant, and made up the Kingdom of Iſrael: Now after this diviſion (which began about the year of the world, 2969.) untill the cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivity of Babylon, and deſtruction of Jeruſalem by <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ucha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>zzar,</hi> there were but twenty Kings of Judah, and of there eight ſuffered a violent death, and of Iſrael before their laſting captivity, 2 <hi>King.</hi> 17. 6.) there were but nineteen Kings, whereof not one feared God among them all, and of theſe nine died a violent death, beſides others impriſoned, cruelly uſed, &amp;c. In England ſince the coming in of the Norman <hi>William</hi> (which is uſually ſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the Conqueſt) there hath been five and twenty Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, of whom nine came to a violent death: and many more of thoſe 109. Kings of Scotland. I ſay it for this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ad, to ſhew what croſſes and calamities do oft times attend great perſons and places, which cauſe their trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles to exceed their comforts, which made <hi>Solomon</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain of the vanity of vanities in all conditions, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 1. &amp; before him his Father <hi>David</hi> ſay, that he <hi>had ſeen an end of all perfection, Pſalm</hi> 19. 96. Nay, ſee how ſomtimes Gods heavy hand goes out againſt a whole great Family, or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ine; thus we find <hi>Ahab</hi> and <hi>Jezabel</hi> guilty of blood, of godly <hi>Nabathe</hi> blood, ſee what became of all that race <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd line, <hi>Ahab</hi> was ſhot to death by a man that ſhot at <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>venture, and timed not at him more then any other, 1 <hi>King.</hi> 22. 34. as he went up againſt <hi>Ramoth-Gilcad,</hi> but
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:47130:16"/> it was purpoſely levelled, fore-told, and directed by God againſt <hi>Ahab,</hi> 1 <hi>King.</hi> 21. 19. as <hi>Elijah</hi> had told the King ere he went up thither; ſo alſo <hi>Micaiah,</hi> 1 <hi>King.</hi> 22. 28. and <hi>Jezabel,</hi> who was wife, mother, and daughter to a King, even ſhe was ſlain, 2 <hi>King.</hi> 29. 33. King <hi>Aha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ziah</hi> ſon to <hi>Ahab,</hi> never recovered of h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s fall through the Lettice, 2 <hi>King.</hi> 1. 2, 16, 17. then <hi>Ahabs</hi> other ſon <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horam</hi> was King of Iſrael, 2 <hi>King</hi> 3. 1. he goes againſt <hi>Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moth-Gilead,</hi> and takes it, which his father <hi>Ahab</hi> could not do, and having received ſome wounds in that ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, he leaves <hi>Jehu</hi> one of his Captains, Commander in chief over his Army <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t <hi>Ramoth-Gilead,</hi> and goes him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to be cured at <hi>Jezreel,</hi> preſently <hi>Jehu</hi> (by Gods ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment, 2 <hi>King.</hi> 9. 1, 2, 3, 7, 8. &amp;c.) drawes all the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my againſt King <hi>Jehoram,</hi> (his King, his Maſter, and his Maſter <hi>Ahabs</hi> ſon) and ſlew him, 2 <hi>King.</hi> 9. 24, 25. and that the blood of <hi>Naboth</hi> which <hi>Ahab</hi> had a hand in was a maine cauſe of all this, appears becauſe it's expreſſed, that in the ſame place where <hi>Naboths</hi> blood was ſhed, both <hi>Ahabs</hi> and <hi>Iehorams</hi> blood was ſpilt, 1 <hi>King.</hi> 21. 19. and 2 <hi>King.</hi> 9. 25, 26. and ſo of <hi>Iezabel,</hi> 2 <hi>King.</hi> 9. 36, 37. <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thaliab</hi> the daughter of <hi>Ahab</hi> was married to <hi>Jehoram</hi> King of Judah, 2 <hi>King.</hi> 8. 16. 17, 18. ſhe was ſlaine, 2 <hi>King.</hi> 11. 16. her huſbands bowells fell out, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 21, 18, 19. none proſpered that medled with that Line, their elder ſons were ſlain, or carried captive by the Philiſtins and Arabians, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 21. 17. and 22. 1. <hi>Ahaziah</hi> King <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habs</hi> grandchild, and ſome think he married againe into that ſtock, 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 8. 27. he joyned with <hi>Jehoram</hi> in that war, and after to viſit him, 2 <hi>King.</hi> 8. 28, 29. he was ſlaine 2 <hi>King.</hi> 9. 27. and 42. of <hi>Ahaziahs</hi> brethren, or kindred of <hi>Ahabs</hi> ſtock were ſlaine, 2 <hi>King.</hi> 10. 14. and ſeventy more of <hi>Ahabs</hi> ſons and grand-children by ſeverall wives were ſlaine, 2 <hi>King.</hi> 10. 1, 7. ſo as none remained of that line and family, 1 <hi>King.</hi> 21. 21. ſee the like of <hi>Baaſha,</hi> another King of Iſrael, his line, 1 <hi>King.</hi> 16. 11.</p>
            <p>Who hath not read the continued ſucceſſion of cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:47130:16"/> that attended <hi>Mary</hi> Queen of Scotland, mother to the late King <hi>James</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> her cradle to her grave? Her father King <hi>James</hi> the fifth, died about the time of her birth, when ſhe was about ſix years old, ſhe was ſent to France in great danger by winds and Engliſh ſhips, there was an agreement 'twixt England and Scotland for a match 'twixt our King <hi>Edward</hi> the ſixth, and her, which breaking on their part, occaſioned the Lord <hi>Protectors</hi> march with an Engliſh Army to Muſcleborough field, where much blood was ſhed, and a Scotch Lord being ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken priſoner, and asked how he liked our wedding with Scotland? ſaid, he liked the match well, but not the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, to fetch a wife with fire and ſword: In France ſhe was married young to <hi>Francis</hi> the <hi>Dolphin of France,</hi> who died ſhortly after of a pain in his ear, then was ſhe <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Omnia fai &amp; nihil mihi pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuit,</hi> ſaid <hi>Sc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verus</hi> the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror, when he was dying; and almoſt all the Roman Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors untill <hi>Conſtantine,</hi> and very many Popes after him, got no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing by all their great ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancement, for the getting whereof they adventured life and limb, and a better thing; <hi>ſed ut citius in terſicerentur,</hi> as <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ban</hi> a wedge to cleave him, and gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments throw him.</note> in great dangers by Sea in her returne back to Scotland, where alſo ſhe found the Scots in Armes, ſhe was there married to <hi>Henry</hi> Lord <hi>Darnley,</hi> (ſon to <hi>Matthew Stuart</hi> Earle of <hi>Lenox)</hi> by whom ſhe had King <hi>Iames,</hi> her huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band was murthered ſoon after King <hi>Iames</hi>'s birth, ſhe was apprehended by the States of Scotland, charged with the murther, and impriſoned, after ſhe eſcaped out of priſon, fled to England where ſhe was priſoner, firſt in one place, and then another, above ſixteen years, and then beheaded at Fotheringay-Caſtle in Northamptonſhire: ſhe deſired to be buried in France, but was buried at Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terburgh, aged ſix and forty years, and yet could not reſt in a grave, her body was taken up again by King <hi>Iames,</hi> and buried at Weſtminſter: Every Crown of Gold is lined with a Crown of Thornes, who almoſt would take up Crowns upon theſe termes? but ſpirituall Princes their comforts in life, death, after death, exceed their croſſes, they have that joy that no man can take from them, that will ſupport them at the ſtake, in the Dun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geon, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>2. There is no Nation where all the Subjects are tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall Princes, but all Chriſts true Subjects, in whoſe hearts
<gap reason="missing" extent="2 pages">
                  <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:47130:17"/> their own Spirit which is one of the greateſt conqueſts, <hi>Prov.</hi> 16. 32. and over afflictions, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. 37.</p>
            <p>9. Temporall Princes be not all of one Line no not in the ſame Kingdome, as in England, ſomtimes the Romans ruled here, ſomtimes the Britains, then Saxons, then Dane<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, then Normans, and ſince the Norman <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam,</hi> ſomtimes his own Race ruled here, then the <hi>Planta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genets,</hi> then the <hi>Tudors,</hi> then the <hi>Stuarts,</hi> and of the four and twenty Kings ſince <hi>William</hi> the Conquerors death, not above ſeven in England that could pretend legally to ſucceed their next Predeceſſors either by lineall or collaterall Title; but the Saints are all of one blood, borne of the blood of God, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 1. 13. of the ſame ſpirit, <hi>Joh.</hi> 3. 5, 6, 8.</p>
            <p>10. Some other Princes were annoynted with externall oyle, though it's generally obſerved, that all the Kings of Iſrael and Judah were not anointed with oyl, though <hi>Saul, David, Solomon,</hi> and ſome others were, nor were the Kings of Judah anointed with the holy oyl where with the High Prieſts were anointed, and which God com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to be made, <hi>Exod.</hi> 30. 23.—33. but with common oyl, though laid up in the Sanctuary: The Scotch Hiſtori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans ſay that externall anointing of their Kings never be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan with them ti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Popery got footing there, (from which they ſay, their Nation was free many years after Chriſt, and kept much purity in Religion) and that King <hi>Edgar</hi> was the firſt ſo anointed there. <hi>Anno</hi> 1098. <note n="*" place="margin">The French Hiſtorians tell much of the holy oyl kept at Reims, yet generally ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge that the firſt King of France that was anoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted was <hi>Pepin,</hi> and that none of the Mero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vignion Line were anointed.</note> (and yet their former Kings were as much, and as truly Gods a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nointed as the later) but all the Saints are Gods Anoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 105. 14, 15. with a ſupernaturall and heavenly Oyl of Grace, 1 <hi>Ioh.</hi> 2. 27. The Apoſtle tells us, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 1. 9. That Chriſt was anointed with the oyl of gladneſſe above his fellows, which notes two things. 1. That all the Saints are Chri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>s fellows, fellow-heirs, fellow-ſufferers, fellow-conquerors &amp;c. 2. That they are anointed with the divine graces that Chriſt is, only in their meaſure, (for of Chriſts fulneſſe they receive grace for grace, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 1. 16.) <hi>Pſal.</hi> 133. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:47130:17"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:47130:18"/>
            <pb n="33" facs="tcp:47130:18"/>
            <p> The next thing is to ſhew you, wherein they are <hi>Princes,</hi> (for, as <hi>Zebah</hi> and <hi>Zalmunna</hi> ſaid to <hi>Gideon</hi> concerning his brethren, <hi>Judg.</hi> 8. 18. <hi>they each one reſemble the children of a King;)</hi> and of this briefly.</p>
            <p n="1">1. They are <hi>Princes</hi> by birth, by the new and ſecond birth, born of the royal blood of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt, Joh.</hi> 1. 12, 13.</p>
            <p n="2">2. They have the vaſt poſſeſſions of Princes <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Abraham</hi> had little, yet he was heir of the whole world; Rom. 4, 13</note> (as before is proved;) <hi>Luther</hi> ſaid, that all the vaſt dominions of the <hi>Turk</hi> was but a ſcrap caſt to a dog; but the Saints dominions are higher, larger, &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="3">3. They have the power of <hi>Princes; As a Prince haſt thou power with God,</hi> ſaid Chriſt to <hi>Jacob, Gen.</hi> 32. 28. <hi>Paul</hi> can do <hi>all things through Chriſt, Phil.</hi> 4. 13. <hi>All things are poſſible to him that beleeveth, Mark</hi> 9. 23. They have pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Hic homo potuit apud de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um quod vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luit,</hi> was ſaid of <hi>Luther;</hi> Saints are the bleſſings of &amp; to a place; Iſaiah 19, 24</note> with God, ſo as to ſtop Lions mouths, quench fire, binde <note place="margin">2 King. 2. 8, 14</note> up the Sea, nay binde the hands of God, <hi>Exod.</hi> 32. 10. And the Queen of <hi>Scots</hi> (before mentioned) ſaid, that ſhe more feared the prayers of Mr <hi>John Knox,</hi> then an Army of 20000 men: So ſaid <hi>Leolin</hi> Prince of <hi>Wales</hi> of another; and the Elector of <hi>Saxony</hi> of the Archbiſhop of <hi>Magdenburgh,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="4">4. They conquer as mighty <hi>Princes; Death,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. 55. <hi>and Hell, Rom.</hi> 8. 1. <hi>and afflictions, Rom.</hi> 8. 37, 38. <hi>Prince of darkneſs, Eph.</hi> 6. 12. <hi>their luſts,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10. 4. <hi>their hearts, Prov.</hi> 16. 32. <hi>Jam.</hi> 4. 7. <hi>Rev.</hi> 2. 26, 27. a greater conqueſt then <hi>Davids</hi> over <hi>Goliah.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. They are clothed as Princes: The Queen in the <hi>Pſalm</hi> was clothed with <hi>gold of Ophir,</hi> yet her beſt clothing was within, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 45. 9, 13. They have robes that none wear but Princes, the perfect merits of Chriſt upon them; They are clothed with the Sun, <hi>Rev.</hi> 12. 1. Chriſts long white robe, <hi>Revel.</hi> 19. 8. and with the ſincere garment of grace within them, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 16. 8. <hi>to</hi> 14. The Scripture calls Chriſts merits <hi>the beſt robe, Luk.</hi> 15. 22. none but Princes wear it.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Fed as Princes; not ſcraps, but Childrens bread, Angels food, fed at the Kings own Table (as <hi>Mephiboſheth;)</hi> They have meat that the world knows not of, as Chriſt ſaid, <hi>Joh.</hi> 4. 32.</p>
            <p n="7">
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:47130:19"/> 7. Served as Princes; Chriſt ſerves them, <hi>Joh.</hi> 13. 4, 5, 6. <hi>Luk.</hi> 22. 27. Angels of Heaven ſerve them, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 1. <hi>ult.</hi> Devils and wicked men are ſcullions to them, to ſcour them, as <hi>Luthers</hi> phraſe was.</p>
            <p n="8">8. Their work is Princes work; not drudgery, but <hi>ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vire Deo est regnare:</hi> Wicked men do the Devils work, ſome without door, as profane men; ſome within doors, as Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cries: The Saints do Gods.</p>
            <p n="9">9. They ſhall judg the world ere long, as great Princes, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6. 3. How many men are converted to God, ſo many Judges are born into the world, and therefore no wonder that they are ſo hated by wicked men: Ere long, <hi>Felix</hi> ſhall be Priſoner, and <hi>Paul</hi> the Judg; <hi>Herod</hi> the Priſoner, and <hi>John Baptist</hi> the Judg; <hi>Pharaoh</hi> the Priſoner, and <hi>Moſes</hi> Judg: <hi>Mat.</hi> 19. 28. <hi>Pareus</hi> obſerves, that Chriſtians uſed to bring their cauſes to be tryed by the Biſhops, as ſuppoſed godlieſt and juſt; after they claimed it as a right, and ſo would be both Biſhops and Princes: Saints ſhall judg without ſin.</p>
            <p n="10">10. They ſhall ere long be crowned in glory as Princes: In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed the Saints in this life are in their nonage. It's chronicled as a great happineſs of a Family in <hi>Ireland</hi> (the Barons of <hi>Hoath,)</hi> that the heirs thereof for 400 years together were always at age before their fathers death: but here the Saints are not at full age till their own death; and then crowned in glory: Onely take heed that we be not children of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom in profeſſion onely, but in truth, elſe we ſhall be caſt out, <hi>Mat.</hi> 8. 12.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu.</hi> If you ask, how ſuch poor ſinful creatures come to be ſuch great Princes?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> I anſwer, 1. By birth, as before, <hi>Joh.</hi> 1. 13. 2. By <note place="margin">Acts 20. 28 Epheſ 1. 14 <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, People of <hi>Gods</hi> purchaſe 1 Pet 2 9 1 Cor. 6, 20</note> marriage, they marry unto the royal line, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 54. 5. 3. By Purchaſe, Chriſt bought it for them, and them for it. 4 By deed of gift, <hi>Luk.</hi> 12. 32. <hi>Edward</hi> the ſixth could not give his Kingdom away, if he could, it had not come, as it did, to Queen <hi>Mary:</hi> but our Father can, and will, both that of grace and glory, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 84. 11.</p>
            <p>Favor me, right honorable and well-beloved, with a little
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:47130:19"/> more of your patience and attention, and I ſhall apply this briefly, and diſpatch the reſt in few words. And,</p>
            <p n="1">1. It ſhews the happineſs and honor of all the Saints; ſuch <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe. </seg>1</label> honor have they all, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 149. 9. They are no baſe or vile perſons, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 15. 4. but mighty Princes. There is not the pooreſt godly man alive would change eſtates with the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt wicked man in the world; for would great Princes change Eſtates with Beggars, every wicked man (though ſwelled as big as <hi>Nimrod</hi> or <hi>Pharaoh)</hi> are Beggars, and live upon the Alms of the Pariſh (as I may ſay,) They are ſpared alive out of Hell awhile, for the <hi>Saints</hi> ſake: God ſpares the Tares for the <hi>Wheats</hi> ſake; and <hi>Sodom</hi> for the <hi>Right<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ous</hi> ſake, (if it be ſpared,) <hi>Job</hi> 22. 10. Nay, wicked men are condemned al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready; They are reprieved, not from Aſſizes till the next Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſizes, but from moment to moment: but the <hi>Saints,</hi> though they walk on foot, as <hi>Solomon</hi> obſerved, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 10. 7. are Princes; They have much in preſent poſſeſſion, and much in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion, happy they; no wonder they would not change, not <hi>Moſes</hi> with <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> not <hi>John Baptist</hi> with <hi>Herod,</hi> not <hi>Paul</hi> with <hi>Felix, &amp;c.</hi> Time is coming, when <hi>Haman</hi> would be glad to be <hi>Mordecai's</hi> Lacky, as old World would have been glad to have been in the place of <hi>Noahs</hi> Dog, when flood came: The <hi>righteous is now more excellent then his neighbor, Prov.</hi> 12. 26. and wicked mens Conſciences convince them now, but much more at the great Day. <hi>Theodoſius</hi> uſed more to glory that he was ſervant of Chriſt, then that he was Emperor of the Eaſt: So King <hi>David</hi> glories that he was Gods ſervant, twice in one Ver<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 116. 16. <hi>Moſes,</hi> though dead, not onely was, but is, ſo: <hi>Joſh.</hi> 1. 2.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The next ſhews how joyful a day the day of our converſion <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe. </seg>2</label> is, it's our Coronation-day, we then enter upon our dominion; it was decreed before Time, purchaſed in the fulneſs of Time, but we are not crowned till our Converſion. In every Town, Pariſh, Village, ſo many as are converted, ſo many Princes are in that Town. <hi>Object.</hi> But I cannot tell the day of my Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion. <hi>Anſ.</hi> But thou canſt tell the day that thou waſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>converted, and God hath wrought a change in thee: A man
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:47130:20"/> knows he was born into this world, though he cannot remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber the day when; and a woman knows that ſhe was married, though ſhe cannot tell juſt the day and hour when it was.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Bleſs God that would look on ſuch poor creatures, and <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe. </seg>3</label> raiſe us out of worſe then the dunghil, and make us great Princes, <hi>Pſa.</hi> 113. 7, 8. Oh that Chriſt would make thoſe Princes, in whom <hi>Satan</hi> once raigned, and bound, more then eighteen years, <hi>Luk.</hi> 13. 16. <hi>&amp;</hi> 11. 21, 22.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Then let us be exhorted to carry and behave our ſelves <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe. </seg>4</label> as Princes.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Cry not for toys and trifles: Was it not a great ſhame for a great Prince to weep and mourn for the loſs of two or <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Monſtroſares eſt ſedes prima vita ima.</hi> Bern.</note> three pins, poynts, or ſarthings? <hi>Jerom</hi> tells of one <hi>Dydimus,</hi> a godly learned Preacher, who was blinde, <hi>Alexander,</hi> a god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly man, comes to him, and asks him, <hi>Are you not ſore trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled and afflicted for want of your ſight? Oh, yes,</hi> ſaid <hi>Dydi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus, it's a great affliction and grief to me:</hi> Then <hi>Alexander</hi> chid him, ſaying, <hi>Hath God given you that which is the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency of an Angel, of an Apostle, and are you troubled for that which Rats, and Mice, and brute beasts have?</hi> So, hath God made us Kings and Princes to God, and ſhall we mourn or murmur for theſe outward trifles? &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Are you Princes? Away then with all baſe employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments: Is it no aſhame to ſee Princes rake the channels, turn Scavengers, ſhovel the dirt? &amp;c. The <hi>Heathen Romans</hi> did conceit that there was a filthy Hag or Witch, called <hi>Lulla,</hi> that ſtrangled their children in the Cradle, ſo that when the Nurſes rocked the children to ſleep, they cryed <hi>Lulla abi, Lulla abi, Lulla</hi> begone, avoyd; whence to this day Nur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes uſe at ſuch times to ſing <hi>Lullabie:</hi> Let all ſpiritual Princes <note place="margin">Iſai. 30. 22</note> ſay to all curſed luſts, Begone, get thee hence: Shall they ſwear, be drunk, worldly? No, remember thou art a hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Prince.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Envy not wicked men: Shall great Princes envy the hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs of poor condemned and reprieved Beggars? I have read of a Souldier, that (upon a ſtrict command of the General, that no Soldier ſhould break into the Vineyards as they march<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:47130:20"/> nor take any thing from that place upon pain of death,) he broke into the Vineyards, and took onely one bunch of Grapes, for which he was condemned; and as he went to execution, was eating of that bunch of Grapes, his fellow-Soldiers chid him, ſaying, <hi>He ought then to minde ſomewhat elſe;</hi> To whom he ſaid, <hi>I beſeech you Sirs do not envy me my Grapes, they will coſt me dear; you would be loath to have them at my rate:</hi> So do not you envy nor murmur at wicked men; alaſs when the reckoning comes, you would be loath to have their ſweet bits at their rate.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Carry noble mindes of Princes: Though Kings are ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by the plough, yet their minds are taken up with higher <note place="margin">Eccleſ. 5; 5</note> matters of State. It is written of our King <hi>Edward,</hi> that he had a burning deſire to go to the holy Land, <hi>Zechar.</hi> 2. 12. (for ſo they called the Land of <hi>Canaan,</hi> though now I think there is no Land more unholy) but being prevented by death, he charged his Son to carry his heart thither: So, though we be below, and trade, and meddle in things here below, yet let our hearts and affections be above: Though we have our Commoration on Earth, let us have our Converſation in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3. 20. which is a ſure evidence that we are riſen a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain already, <hi>Col.</hi> 3. 1, 2.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Let us keep company with Princes, even godly men: Would it not be a great ſhame to ſee the honorable Judges of Aſſize go off the Bench, leave the Society of the Juſtices and Gentry of the Country, and onely keep company with the Priſoners at the Bar? Sheep and Wolves, Princes and baſe Peaſants, have ſmall converſe together: <hi>Have no fellowſhip with the unfruitful works of darkneſs, Eph.</hi> 5. 11.</p>
            <p n="6">6. If you are Princes, contend not for every toy; <hi>Regium eſt malé audire quum bené feceris.</hi> Jeſus Chriſt is <hi>Prince of Life, Acts</hi> 23. 15. <hi>Prince of Peace, Iſai.</hi> 9. 6. <hi>Prince of the Kings of the Earth, Dan.</hi> 8. 25. <hi>Rev.</hi> 1. 5. and he hath made us great <hi>Princes,</hi> and ſhall we contend for every quarrel, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6. 1. <hi>to</hi> 7. It's reported of Judg <hi>Dyer,</hi> that when any petty Controverſies came before him, eſpecially of poor men, he uſed to ſay, <hi>That either the parties were wilful, or their neighbors uncharitable.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="7">
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:47130:21"/> 7. In the cauſe and way of God go on undauntedly, and with princely courage, yea, both in doing and ſuffering for Chriſt: And here give me leave to apply it more parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly; and, 1. To you my Lords, whom God hath been pleaſed to call to theſe publique places; and that you may go on undauntedly for God and your Country, Look, 1. That your principles be ſound and upright, elſe however you judg men now, yet poor men will judg you another day, when all the <hi>Saints</hi> ſhal judg the world. 2. Look you be upright in your ways; uprightneſs hath boldneſs: do not ſteer your courſe according to friends, or foes, or mens corrupt humors. It's ſaid of <hi>Baldwin</hi> the <hi>French</hi> Lawyer, that he had <hi>Religionem Ephemeram,</hi> every day a new Religion, but conſtant to none; <note place="margin">Beza.</note> and therefore ſaith <hi>Beza,</hi> he became <hi>Deo hominibuſque quos toties fefellerat, inviſus.</hi> Some of you have read of a very great Courtier of this Land, who was a great Favorite to King <hi>Henry</hi> the eighth a Papiſt, to King <hi>Edward</hi> the ſixth a <hi>Proteſtant,</hi> to Queen <hi>Mary</hi> a Papiſt, to Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> a <hi>Protestant,</hi> and kept both great favor and places; being ask<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed how he could do ſo, he anſwered, I always imitated <note place="margin">L. <hi>Pawlet.</hi>
               </note> the Willow, and not the Oak, was ready to bow and bend to the luſts of great men, and humors of the Times, as one not tyed to <hi>John Baptists</hi> Conſcience, but giving elbow-room to <hi>Jeroboams</hi> policy, &amp;c. I can tell you of a Judg (God ever deliver you from his ſteps) that raiſed a moſt ſtrange concluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on from honeſt Premiſſes, I mean, <hi>Pilate, Luk.</hi> 23. 14, 15, 16. who ſaith concerning Chriſt, <hi>I have examined him, and found no fault in this man, therefore I will chastiſe him:</hi> Unjuſt Judg! nay therefore chaſtiſe him not: Or, as it is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated by <hi>John,</hi> cap. 19. 6. <hi>I finde no fault in him, therefore take ye him, and crucifie him:</hi> nay rather ought he to reſcue and deliver him. <hi>Epaminondas,</hi> a <hi>Heathen</hi> man, being poor, and tempted with great preſents, uſed to ſay, if the cauſe was good, he would do it without a bribe, becauſe it was good; if bad, not for a world.</p>
            <p>3. Look your ends be right; the Devil knows that that is a prevailing temptation wherewith he thought to have undone
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:47130:21"/> 
               <hi>Job,</hi> when all other ſhafts failed, <hi>doth Job ſerve God for nought?</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Job.</hi> 1. 9.</note> as if he had ſome by-ends in it: This undid <hi>Jehu,</hi> who executed judgment ſeverely on the houſe of <hi>Ahab,</hi> which God com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded, and yet God revenged all that very blood upon <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hu's</hi> houſe, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 1. 4. becauſe of <hi>Jehu's</hi> by-end in the work.</p>
            <p>Secondly, A word to you Right worſhipful and worthy <note place="margin">2. Take heed leſt any of you favor drunken Alehouſes to uphold your Rents &amp; price of Corn, or Your Clerks fee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Holy Mr <hi>Fenner</hi> ſaith that he heard a Clerk of the Aſſizes ſay, that he was glad there were ſo many <hi>rogues,</hi> becauſe he got more money.</note> Juſtices of peace; I pray you pull out the beams out of your own eyes firſt: be not you guilty of thoſe vices, which you ought to puniſh in others, ſo ſhall you go on with courage. You ſee at theſe Aſſizes divers devouring Wolves arraigned, would you purſue them to their den, you ſhould finde moſt of this to ſpring from, and be hatched at, debuched Alehouſes: I pray you know neither friend or ſoe; Juſtice is pictured blinde as to mens perſons, but quick-ſighted in cauſes: Shall I puniſh my friend, for whom ſuch a one ſpeaks, an old ſervant to my Father, to my Wife, Son? &amp;c. No, nor your foe neither: With all my heart ſpare your friend, but puniſh the Malefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor; Teach men in your Ridings and Seſſions that <hi>Norman</hi> diſtinction that <hi>William</hi> the firſt taught an <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Odo,</hi> bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to K. <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam,</hi> Earl of <hi>Kent,</hi> and Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of <hi>Bayeux</hi> in <hi>Normandy.</hi>
               </note> Earl of <hi>Kent,</hi> whom the King would puniſh for his foul miſdemeanors; the Earl being alſo Biſhop of <hi>Bayeux</hi> in <hi>France,</hi> pleaded he did not do the fault as he was Earl, but as he was Biſhop, (and ſo then not under the temporal Juriſdiction;) To whom the King replyed, neither do I puniſh you as a Biſhop, but as an Earl; however the party was puniſhed: ſpare your friend, yea and your foe alſo, if you will, but puniſh the Malefactor.</p>
            <p>3. To you Gentlemen of the long robe, (to whom I ſpake free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <note place="margin">3. <hi>Britania redi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viva.</hi>
               </note> yet truly here, the laſt Aſſizes; and therefore no more now but this,) plead now, as you may, with courage, ſtand up at laſt, and have Chriſt plead your cauſe: I do not ſay, when or while cauſes are dark and doubtful, but when it clearly and plainly appears that the cauſe is untrue and unjuſt; Do not do your beſt or worſt to colour it over, and to cauſe unjuſtice to be done (or elſe it ſhall not want your furtherance;) Think not that this is enough to ſay, Am I for the <hi>Plaintiff,</hi> or <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendant,</hi> (no matter which,) and when you ſee the cauſe naught,
<gap reason="missing" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page missing〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:47130:22"/>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:47130:22"/> body, more diſtempers ſtill do appear, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 7. 1. Thus in <hi>Christs</hi> Time, <hi>Scribes, Phariſees, Herodians;</hi> in <hi>Apostles</hi> days, in <hi>Primitive</hi> Times, <hi>Ebion, Cerinthus,</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Arrius</hi> his Hereſie was condemned by the Councel of <hi>Nice,</hi> Anno D. 330. <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedonius</hi> by the Councel of <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> Anno D. 383 <hi>Athanaſius</hi> roſe up migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily againſt <hi>Arrius</hi> in <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantines</hi> days; and <hi>Baſil</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Maced.</hi> in <hi>Theodoſius</hi> days. <hi>Neſtori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned by the Councel of <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſus,</hi> an. 490 and <hi>Eutiches</hi> by the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel of <hi>Calcedo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> Anno 456 When <hi>Auſtin</hi> mightily ſpred the Goſpel, <hi>Pelagius</hi> (alias <hi>Morgan)</hi> ſpred His Errors, (both of them were born on one day, <hi>Auſtin</hi> in <hi>Africk,</hi> and <hi>Pelagius</hi> in <hi>Wales.)</hi> In our flight from <hi>Rome,</hi> ſaith Mr <hi>Bayly,</hi> ſome heretofore ſtopt too ſoon, as the <hi>Lutherans;</hi> and after them <hi>Cranmer, Rid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley, &amp;c.</hi> who leſt too much Popery; And others ran too far (ſaith he) as <hi>Anabap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts;</hi> and after them <hi>Bolton, Brown, Barrow &amp;c.</hi> and the Browniſts; Sure I am if the late Biſhops ſtopt too ſoon, many now adays run as much too far. <hi>Mos iſte in Eccleſia ſemper viguit, ut quo quiſque fo et religioſior co promptius novellis adinventi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onibus contrairet;</hi> ſaith <hi>Vincent. Lirinenſ.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Arrius, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedonius, Neſtorius, Eutyches, Pelagius;</hi> in <hi>Luthers</hi> days many Sects, <hi>Anabaptiſm, Antinomianiſm;</hi> in <hi>Calvins, Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetus:</hi> but) this is ſad, that what was owned by all to be profain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs twelve years ago, (as to ſwear commonly, not to pray, nor confeſs ſin, nor ſanctifie Sabbath, nor frequent Gods Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances, to deny the <hi>Scriptures, &amp;c.)</hi> if a man now do the ſame things, and ſay he holds an Opinion, or it is his Opinion that he may do thus, then it ſhould be accounted no profane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, but Religion? Curſed Errors draw the beſt ſpirits (ſaith holy and learned Mr <hi>Hooker</hi> of <hi>New-England)</hi> from the heart to the head, turn Religion into a Diſpute, and make it onely a matter of queſtions and words, and eat out, in very many, the very heart of godlineſs. It was the great grief of holy Mr <hi>Burroughs,</hi> not long before his death, that he could not ſee that practical power of godlineſs in the profeſſors of theſe days, which he ſaw in thoſe that dyed immediately be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore theſe Times began; but that we ſeem (ſaid he) to have more light, but leſs life. Oh this doth not beſeem ſpiritual <hi>Princes of Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> A forraign Writer, three years ago, to our ſhame, publiſhed, <hi>Anglia his quatuor annis facta eſt colluvies &amp; lerna omnium Errorum ac Sectarum, nulla à condito orbe Provincia tam parvo ſpatio tot monstroſas Hae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſes protulit, atque haec, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>5. Let this be a Caveat to all perſons, to take heed they of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>5</label> no injuries to godly men, for they are ſpiritual <hi>Princes:</hi> You know how dangerous <hi>Scandalum magnatum</hi> and <hi>Cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men</hi>
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:47130:23"/> 
               <hi>laeſae Majestatis</hi> were accounted to be; Take heed how you rail againſt or affront a godly man for godlineſs ſake, truly you kick againſt the pricks, Chriſt will own it, <hi>Saul, Saul, why perſecuteſt thou me? Act.</hi> 9. Theſe are Gods anointed, touch them not at your peril, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 105. 14. They are the dearly beloved of Gods Soul, <hi>Jerem.</hi> 12. 7. Gods <hi>Hephzi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bah, Iſai.</hi> 62. 4. Gods delight is in them; Theſe are the Spouſe of Chriſt, and Chriſt will ſay, Will you force the Queen before me, as <hi>Ahaſhuerus</hi> ſaid of <hi>Haman, Eſth.</hi> 7. 8. Theſe are the Lords portion, take heed what you do to theſe men, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>The ſixth Uſe is for Comfort to all the Saints, becauſe they <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe. </seg>6</label> are ſpiritual <hi>Princes:</hi> 1. <hi>Kings</hi> and <hi>Princes</hi> are not uſually tryed at an ordinary Court, but ſome ſpecial Court for them: Truly godly men ſhall not be tryed, 1. At mans Bar, not ſtand to mans day <note n="*" place="margin">1 Cor. 4. 3 <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. When <hi>Wood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roof</hi> the ſheriff called Mr <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers</hi> (our Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomartyr) He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retique, that ſhal be known ſaid <hi>Rogers,</hi> at the day of Judgment.</note>, who uſually rail againſt them, and mock them: 3. Nor at the Bar of ſtrict Juſtice, but at the Chancery of free mercy, their debts being payd, perſons covered in Chriſt, and their Husband their Judg. Secondly, Theſe <hi>Princes</hi> have two of the beſt Kingdoms that we ever heard of, the one of Grace, the other of Glory; that whiles others glory of Corn, Wine, Oyl, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 4. 7. and petty Mannors, the Saints may ſay as the King of <hi>France</hi> commanded his Herauld to cry ſtill, <hi>King of France, King of France;</hi> ſo they, <hi>Heirs of Grace and Glory.</hi> Thirdly, <hi>Princes</hi> are an honour to the place where they are born and bred: So <hi>Pſal.</hi> 87. 5, 6. Of <hi>Sion</hi> it ſhall be ſaid, this and that man was born in her: So many godly men in a Town, ſo many <hi>Princes</hi> in a Town. It is an honor to <hi>Boston</hi> in <hi>Lincolnſhire</hi> that learned and holy Mr <hi>Fox</hi> (that wrote the Book of <hi>Martyrs)</hi> was born there; to <hi>Mancheſter,</hi> that heavenly Mr <hi>Bradford</hi> the Martyr was born there; to <hi>Dean</hi> and <hi>Leigh</hi> in <hi>Lancaſhire,</hi> that <hi>George Marſh</hi> the godly Martyr was born in the firſt, and <hi>Jeffrey Hurſt</hi> in the latter; and Mr <hi>Robert Bolton</hi> at <hi>Blackborn</hi> in the ſame County; Mr <hi>William Perkins</hi> at <hi>Marſton</hi> in <hi>War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wick-ſhire;</hi> Holy Mr <hi>Latimer</hi> at <hi>Thirkeſſon</hi> in <hi>Leiceſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhire;</hi> Martyr <hi>Cranmer</hi> at <hi>Arſelacton</hi> in <hi>Nottinghamſhire;</hi>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:47130:23"/> Doctor <hi>Willet</hi> at <hi>Ely</hi> in <hi>Cambridg-ſhire;</hi> Mr <hi>Whateley</hi> at <hi>Bambury</hi> in <hi>Oxfordſhire,</hi> 
               <note n="a" place="margin">Many wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy men born in <hi>Lancaſhire,</hi> Dr <hi>Whitaker,</hi> Mr <hi>Nouel,</hi> Mr <hi>Bentley,</hi> Mr R. <hi>Balton,</hi> Mr <hi>Bradford, George Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſh, Jeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frey Hurſt, &amp;c.</hi> In <hi>Devonſh re</hi> Biſhop <hi>Juel,</hi> Dr <hi>Reynolds.</hi> In <hi>Northumberland</hi> Biſhop <hi>Ridley</hi> Martyr. <hi>Cumberland</hi> Archbiſhop <hi>Grindal. Weſtmoreland</hi> Mr <hi>Gilpin. Buck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inghamſhire</hi> Dr <hi>Humphred. Shropſhire</hi> Dr <hi>Holland. Hampſhire</hi> Mr <hi>Philpot. Kent</hi> Mr <hi>Ed. Deering. Nottinghamſhire</hi> Archbiſhop <hi>Cranmer;</hi> both Mr <hi>Chappels, &amp;c.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>7. In all theſe hurryings and clatterings of the Times, while <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe, </seg>7</label> every one is contending about Kings and Princes at home and abroad, ſuch ſtirs, plottings and actings about them, and about Government in Church and <hi>State,</hi> let us cry to God, that we may be, and content our ſelves to be, <hi>ſpiritual Princes to Chriſt,</hi> to raign over our luſts, and to have the Government of Chriſt in our hearts: Let this be our greateſt contention and ſtrife; and beg direction from God for them, in whoſe hands is the power of ſetling external Governors and Government. Take heed we be not of thoſe that ſay in our hearts, <hi>We will not have Chriſt to raign over us, Luk.</hi> 19. 37. Content not our ſelves that we are related to godly men, heavenly Princes: <hi>John</hi> of <hi>Valoys</hi> was Son, Uncle, Brother, Father to a King, yet himſelf was never King; ſo here—</p>
            <p>8. Labor what we can the advance and propagation of the <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe. </seg>8</label> Goſpels Miniſtry; It's the means, through Gods Mercy, to beget <hi>Princes to God</hi> in every town and place where it comes: Follow it to <hi>Ireland, Wales,</hi> the <hi>Northern Counties, &amp;c.</hi> with your prayers; yea, into the dark corners of the world, that Chriſt may have <hi>Princes</hi> in all the Earth: This is the means whereby thou mayſt come to have thy Son a crowned King, and thy Daughter a crowned <hi>Queen</hi> in glory. Follow the Goſpel with thy prayers into <hi>America;</hi> How do the fields there begin to look white to the Harveſt? how doth the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of Heaven begin there by the <hi>native Indians</hi> to ſuffer vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olence? God grant the event may never be the taking the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel from us (where too many ſeem weary of the <hi>Scripture, Ordinances, Duties, &amp;c.</hi> and loath the <hi>Manna)</hi> to give it to them. How doth the Goſpels ſucceſs there rejoyce us, eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly if they be poſterity of the <hi>Iews,</hi> as many affirm that they are!</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:47130:24"/>
            <p> 9. The next Uſe is for Tryal: It's dangerous laying claim to Kingdoms when men have no good Title. Our Chronicles <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Straw, Cade, Tiler &amp;c.</hi> Kings are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid of times; <hi>Herod</hi> the great put to death 14000 infants, as <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſephus</hi> writes, with intent to have killed the King of the <hi>Jews,</hi> and did ſlay His <hi>three ſons, Alexander Ariſtobul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>s, Antipato<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> His virtuous wife <hi>Maria<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ne</hi> for fear of loſing His Kingdom. Zec. 14. 20</note> afford many inſtances hereof, and what it coſt them in the end; and is it nothing to claim a Kingdom of Heaven without title?</p>
            <p n="1">1. Art thou ſpiritually anointed? (as we have ſaid,) <hi>Pſal.</hi> 105. 15. 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 2. 27. Oyl, 1. Softens, 2. Heals, 3. That Oyl wherewith Kings were anointed, had a ſweet perfume, &amp;c. So, 1. Is thy heart ſoftened? doth grace ſink as oyl <hi>(Pſa.</hi> 109. 18.) into thy heart, or haſt thou onely ſwimming notions in thy head, or ſome outſide reformation onely? The Soul was firſt in ſinning, in converting, in reſurrection; doth grace pierce thither? is thy heart ſincere in what thou doſt? A godly man hath an imbred, gradual, partial, unwilling bemoaned hardneſs of heart, which he complains of, groans under, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 63. 17. but not a total, wilful, unſenſible hardneſs, which ruines, <hi>Zec.</hi> 7. 12. 2. Art thou healed in ſome meaſure from the raigning and dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning power of ſin? <hi>Rom.</hi> 7. <hi>ult.</hi> 3. Is thy life more ſweet and ſavory? thy ſpeeches, practices? Is Holineſs written upon them?</p>
            <p n="2">2. Is thy minde princely, ſet upon <hi>things above, Col.</hi> 3 1. like <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niels</hi> windows towards <hi>Jeruſalem?</hi> It is not for you (ſaid <hi>Cleopatra</hi> to M. <hi>Antony)</hi> to fiſh for gudgeons, but for Caſtles and Kingdoms; Are our mindes altogether ſet on, and drowned in the <hi>Earth?</hi> are we <hi>ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rigenae f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>atres,</hi> inhabitants of the <hi>Earth, Rev.</hi> 12. 12. (oppoſed to the dwellers in Heaven) whoſe names are written in <hi>the Earth, Jer.</hi> 17. 13 and like <hi>Domitian</hi> follow catching of Flies? Sure then we yet are not ſpiritual Princes; for if ſuch, our mindes would run upon our <hi>Fath<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r, Mother, Country, Houſe,</hi> and <hi>Brethren</hi> above.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Haſt thou got a princely conqueſt over thy luſts, ſo that they reign not over thee? and that as well over that inſide and ſpiritual wickedneſs (which is perhaps <hi>minoris infamiae,</hi> but <hi>majoris reatus)</hi> as well as viſible and ſhameful tranſgreſſions, which fear or ſhame may reſtrain, though the root of the matter be ſtill within as unmortified as before; A godly man is like <hi>Brutus</hi> his ſtaff, <hi>Cujus intus ſolidum aurum corneo valebatur cortice,</hi> gold within and horn without; or like the Ark<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> gold within, goats hair without, &amp;c. I ſhould have given you more evidences of ſpiritual Princes, and of Gods hidden ones, <hi>Pſal:</hi> 83. 3. their title to a Kingdom; as alſo more Uſes; and a third Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine yet remains behind; But the glaſs hath over-run me; and I have learned from <hi>Luther, Cum vides attentiſſime audire populum, conclude &amp;c.</hi> When thou ſeeſt thine Hearers (ſaith he) moſt attentive, then con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude; <hi>eo alacriores redibunt,</hi> ſo they will return more cheerfully the next time; I add no more therefore, but only conclude as <hi>Cyril</hi> doth his <hi>preface</hi> to his <hi>Catechiſm, Meum eſt docere, veſtrum auſcultare, Dei proficere; Paul</hi> may plant, and <hi>Apollos</hi> water, and now the great God give the increaſe.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:47130:24"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
